Hey, everyone.
大家好
Sorry, starting slightly late.
抱歉 稍微迟到了
Had to run from one meeting to the other.
我得从一个会赶到另一个会
Let me get on Twitch on my laptop
我在这台笔记本上登录 Twitch
so I can see all the great comments that are going to come in.
这样我就能看到大家的精彩评论了
I hate Twitch.
我讨厌 Twitch
Okay.
好的
pwn college.
pwn学院
All right.
好的
We are live.
我们直播开始啦
Cool.
酷！
All right.
好的
So...
所以……
Who's finished all of the ARM-ROP challenges?
谁完成了全部的ARM-ROP挑战？
No, none of you?
没有人完成吗？
They can't see.
他们看不见
Two of you.
两个人
Is that actually true, the two of you?
真的只有你们两个完成了？
What?
什么？
I don't know.
我不知道
It says only one solve right here.
这里写着只有一个人解决了
So it sounds like not all of you have done it.
看来你们两个不是都完成了
Some of you?
有些人完成了吗？
I've done a bunch.
我做了不少
Yeah, but all of them.
对 但我说的是全部
Is a bunch all?
很多是全部吗？
That's what I was asking.
我就是想问这个
I create the challenges.
我负责设计挑战
I do not need to solve them.
我不需要解决它们
Cool.
行
Okay, so what we're going to do for 3-1-a, oh
好的 接下来我们来看看 3-1-a
so there are some questions about the static binary ROP.
有人问静态二进制 ROP
This is, there's fundamentally, I think
我觉得
no unintended ways of solving this.
没有其他意料外的解法
So you can solve stat
你可以
like the idea is you have all of libc statically linked into your binary.
二进制文件中静态链接了整个 libc
There's absolutely, I didn't even bother looking at is this solvable
我都不用看，这题绝对能解
because it's clearly solvable.
因为很明显是可解的
There's like so many gadgets in there
里面有很多 gadgets
and there's so many functions in libc that you can reuse.
而且 libc 中有许多可以重用的函数
So you have like a ret to libc style thing
当你有 ret2libc 这样的方法
that's absolutely totally awesome.
那真是太爽了
So don't feel like
别觉得
like as long as
只要
there's not a way to completely bypass the challenge and just get a flag.
没有办法绕过题目，拿到flag
That would be the only unintended solution for this one.
那将是唯一的意外解法
There's literally so many ways you could pop that challenge.
除此之外，有许多方法能解决这题
And then, so what we'll do with level-3-1-a-gcc
接下来 我们来做一下 3-1-a-gcc
which is now very clear that it's hard
很明显难度很大
because it says it in the name.
因为名子已经说明了
What we'll do here is I will relax.
我们这里会放松一些
So I extended this a week so you have another week to work on this
我把这个延了一周 你们有更多时间来完成它
because I thought it was actually great of like
我觉得这样挺好
Seeing these challenges that are accidentally hard
这些题不小心弄的挺难
like I didn't intend for them to be hard
我原本没打算让它们这么难
but it turns out they're hard but not impossible.
但它们确实很难 不过并非不可能
So you have to actually learn things by applying them
所以你们需要通过实践来学习
and this happens all the time when finding vulnerabilities in real stuff.
在真实系统中找漏洞时  这种情况经常出现
Guess what? There's not somebody that conveniently puts little gadgets in for you to use.
没人会为你准备好现成的gadget
You have whatever is there.
你得有什么就用什么
So I extended it a week so you can work on it more.
所以我把期限延长了一周 给你们更多时间研究
The other thing I'm going to do
另外 我会
is relax the academic integrity policy for this challenge.
放宽题目的学术诚信要求
So feel free.
所以不要拘束
I'll also let Zolotol on the Discord act as an unofficial TA
我还会让 Discord 上的 Zolotol 作为非正式助教
so he can drop hints
给大家提供提示
and guide people as breadcrumbs through this
引导大家
so that that way you can kind of we'll solve it together.
算是我们一起来解决它
And then as the outcome of this
这样最终结果是
what I'd like is for you all to discuss.
希望你们能一起讨论
Once we've solved it
等我们解决了题目
what's a good hint that we can put in the description
找到一个能放到描述里的好的提示
to help guide people to the solution
能引导大家找到解题方法
but not necessarily give things away?
但又不至于直接透露答案
I think for my own hint of talking to Zolotol, it's...
我和 Zolotol聊时，的提示是
Is everybody pronouncing that right?
读对了吗？
Zolotol.
Zolotol
Okay, that was just from memory.
好的 这完全是凭记忆的
Basically, if you can pwn this static binary ROP
如果你能攻破这个静态二进制 ROP
you can definitely pwn this.
你肯定也能攻破
So if you think about how can I...
所以你想想我怎么能
get information like I have in static, the static binary ROP.
获取类似静态二进制 ROP 中的信息
You have libc built into the binary
静态二进制文件中内置了 libc
so you know where all the gadgets are.
所以你知道所有 gadgets 的位置
But if you can find out where libc is
但如果你能找到 libc 的地址
you can also use all the stuff that's in libc.
你也可以使用 libc 中的所有功能
So I think from there you can start with that.
所以你可以从这里开始
Let's chat about it online.
我们在线上讨论吧
We can talk about it there.
我们可以在那里讨论
I'm confident that as a group you will find a path forward.
我相信 作为团队 你们会找到前进的方向
Does that sound good?
这听起来怎么样？
No riots on the
这边没有抗议吧
they're threatening to riot on Twitch
他们在 Twitch 上扬言要抗议
but I can't tell if that's one of you in class
我不知道有没有教室里的人
and this was your secret way of... voicing your opinion.
这是你们秘密表达意见的方式
No, no, no.
不 不 不
I'm not touching the binary.
我不碰那个二进制
It's salt.
它是
So the idea is solve it.
所以关键是，要解决它
And it doesn't have to be the one way.
不一定只有一种方法
I'm actually, as I was talking
事实上 在我说的时候
I think there's multiple ways of approaching it.
我觉得有多种方法可以解决
I think the general approach that Zolotol took
我觉得 Zolotol 用的方法
is one that you can apply as well.
你也可以试试
So yeah, but no, we're not relaxing anything.
是的，不过 我们不会放松要求
Cool.
好的
Okay.
行
Okay, the next thing we're going to do, so we are, that hint sucks.
好吧 接下来我们要做的 这个提示真烂
Leaking libc is the hard part.
泄露 libc 是最难的
Is it though?
是吗？
I don't know.
我不知道
People can do it. is it hard?
有人能做到。 难吗？
Yeah, see?
对吧？
Anyways, you can figure it out.
总之 你能想出来的
You strong apes strong together.
猩猩们，团结就是力量（猩球崛起）
You can do it.
你们能做到
I guarantee it.
我保证
And actually, honestly, this is a pretty good...
说实话 这相当不错...
simulation of what it's like working on a team
模拟了团队合作的感觉
when you're trying to exploit something.
当你试图利用某些东西时
Feel free, completely talk about hard level-3-1-a-gcc.
随意些 聊聊 hard-3-1-a-gcc
We'll use the applied vulnerability research channel.
我们用应用漏洞研究频道交流
You don't have to do it in the class one
你不必在第一节课上完成
because there's other people online that are also struggling with this.
因为网上也有其他人卡在这里
In the applied vulnerability research channel
在应用漏洞研究频道
all bets are off on that one.
打开了所有限制
Feel free, brainstorm ideas.
随意些 集思广益
Let's collaboratively work towards something there.
让我们在那里合作 共同完成任务
I think together you can figure it out.
我相信，一起能找到解决办法
I am confident.
我有信心
Okay, that's great.
好的 太好了
And then the next thing I was going to do, what I realized
接下来我打算做的是 我意识到
so it's taking a little bit
这需要一点时间
so to update you on where we are infrastructure-wise
更新一下我们的基础设施情况
so I want you to be able to run and hack stuff without needing a Mac.
我希望大家能在不需要 Mac 的情况下，对mac进行黑客行为
It turns out the state of emulation and virtualization of Mac hardware on non-Mac hardware
结果发现，目前针对在非mac硬件下的，mac硬件仿真
is not what I thought it was.
并不如我想象的那样
There was some nice proof of concept GitHub repos out there that you can find
github上有一些不错的相关概念验证项目
but these... don't work well when you deviate from what they do.
但当你和给定步骤不一致时，效果就不太好
They basically have gotten a Mac OS kernel to boot up and run Bash
基本上，他们会启动一个 Mac OS 内核并运行 Bash
but when you try to run anything else
但当你尝试运行
that's not what they already have installed.
他们没安装的程序时
Like, I'm sure you guys want to compile things with Clang
比如说 你们肯定想用 Clang 编译程序
and debug things with LLDB.
用 LLDB 调试
It causes a kernel infinite loop
这会导致内核无限循环
and I'm not going to debug why this is happening
我不会去调试为什么会发生这种情况
because that would be insane
因为这会让人疯掉
because even if you fix that one thing
因为即使你解决了这个问题
there'll be a thousand other things.
还会有成千上万的其他问题
So the...
所以 这...
What's going on there?
那边出了什么事？
held for aggression.
直播被暂停
What does this even mean?
这到底是什么意思啊？
Sorry, I don't understand Twitch moderation.
抱歉我不懂 Twitch 审核机制
So that, I think we will launch on Wednesday with a thing
所以 我觉得我们会在周三推出这个东西
but it's going to require actual physical ARM
这需要 ARM 物理设备
like Apple Silicon devices
比如 苹果芯片设备
that we will set up in an environment
我们会设置好一个环境
that hopefully will be transparent to you
希望能让你们无感
and you'll just be able to use pwn college
你们直接能在pwn college上用
and you'll get dropped into an ARM
然后直接接入 ARM 环境
into a Mac thing when you're doing this XNU stuff.
接入一个 Mac设备，在黑 XNU 内核时
We'll see.  I'll hopefully show that on Wednesday
到时自见分晓，我希望能在周三展示给大家
or show how close we're getting there.
或者展示我们已经接近完成了
But in the meantime
与此同时
what I realize is one of the things that would be fun is looking at
我意识到，这样可能会很有趣
popping and exploiting other targets that are more real world.
就是，攻击利用更贴近现实世界中的目标
So going beyond kind of what you've been doing in Pwn College,
所以 我们要超越在 Pwn College 里做的
going a little bit closer towards specifically like CTF style challenges
更接近 CTF 风格的挑战
or maybe even real world software
或者甚至是现实世界的软件
kind of like what real world CTF does if you've ever done that.
就像实际的 CTF 比赛一样 如果你参加过的话
It is currently not...
它现在还没有……
I don't think it's quite working yet
我觉得它还不是很好用
but I have a challenge that I ported from...
但我准备了一个题目 它来自……
Where is it?
它在哪里？
CTF Archive.
CTF 档案
From DEF CON 2018.
来自 2018 年的 DEF CON
I'm not logged in.
我没有登录
What?
什么？
Oh, man.
哎呀 糟糕
Somebody should file a bug report.
有人得报个 bug
So This will be live in the AVR thing
这个会放在 AVR 里
so you won't have to find it in here.
所以你不用在这里找了
It's a prior CTF challenge
这是个之前的 CTF 挑战题目
so it makes sense to live in here.
所以放在这里挺合理的
So I created a challenge back in 2018 called www
2018 年我创建了一个叫 www 的挑战
and let's start it
我们开始吧
and just kind of show you.
我来给你演示一下
Okay, so did that work?
好的 这样行吗？
So this is basically a crazy challenge.
这可以说是一个疯狂的挑战
Yeah, anyways, I'm just going to run it.
嗯 不管怎样 我来运行一下
That's not right.
这不对
Oh, you may not be able to read that.
哦 你可能看不到
Okay.
好的
You have to give it a URL.
你得给它一个网址
You actually don't have internet access
环境里没有网络
so I wouldn't put it in an actual URL.
所以我不会放进真正的 URL
And this was a challenge that we...
这是我设计的一个挑战……
yeah, that I created for DEF CON Qualls 2018.
是的 我为 2018 年的 DEF CON 资格赛创建的挑战
The teams hit it over a socket
各团队通过socket连接访问它
so it was a socket connection
是一个socket连接
and then after that
然后
this is the only output that they saw.
这就是他们看到的唯一输出
And you just get cryptic things like booting up
你只会看到类似启动这样的神秘信息
and it takes a while.
它需要一点时间
This is a, I'll just like talk for a while.
那我就聊一会
I don't want to give a ton of the fun away
不想把所有好玩的都剧透了
but then you'll get messages
然后你会收到一些信息
where it's storing screenshots into the tmp directory.
显示它正在将截图保存到/tmp目录
So this is for you to actually know what's going on.
这样你就能知道发生了什么
So if we rsync
我们用 rsync
since I got that working.
因为我跑通了这个
Okay, that's some other file.
好的 这是一些其他的文件
Okay, so open.
好的 打开
So you start seeing stuff like this.
你能看到类似的内容
And I guess it's the same stuff.
我想这是同样的内容
All right, we'll let it boot up.
好的 我们让它慢慢启动
So in the actual challenge
在实际挑战中
because obviously I can't just drop stuff
因为显然我不能直接丢东西进去
you would get base64 encoded things that you had to decode
你会收到Base64编码的东西，然后你要解码
and then realize it was a PNG.
然后你才会意识到那是个 PNG 文件
As you look at it more and more
随着你深入了解
you will find out...
你会发现……
Let's see.
我们来看看
Yeah, so let's see.
嗯 我们来看看
We can dig into this a little bit.
我们可以深入研究一下
This actually feeds in a little bit of what we're going to do today.
这其实和我们今天要做的有点关系
So we see the NeXT Mach operating system, NeXT Mach 3.3,
我们看到NeXT Mach操作系统，NeXT Mach 3.3
information on physical memory,
关于物理内存的信息
yada, yada, yada, Ethernet devices, checking disks.
等等 以太网设备 检查磁盘
What does this look like to you all?
大家觉得这看起来像什么？
Some kind of what?
是什么？
Yeah, some kind of OS is booting up
是的 某个操作系统正在启动
and it's just outputting data, right?
它会输出数据 对吧？
This is every time you run your Linux thing
每次你启动 Linux 时都是这样
and it's just like, Starting some services.
就像这样 启动一些服务
This is what takes a while.
这会花点时间
So it's going to do that.
所以它会做这个
It'll give us some output.
它会输出一些信息
It's still booting.
它还在启动中
I should have preloaded this.
我应该提前加载好这个
Actually, I think I did.
实际上，我加载过了
No, I just deleted all those screenshots.
不 我刚刚删了那些截图
That was silly.
真傻
Sometimes this kind of doesn't work
有时候它会失败
but I'll explain it in a second about why.
但我一会儿解释为什么
Okay.
好的
This is a good reminder.
这是个很好的提醒
Whenever you run a demo live, you should pre-cache the data
现场演示时 最好预先缓存数据
so you don't have to do this
就不会像现在这样了
and you could just go to things instead of making up stuff.
你可以直接演示 而不是临时编造
rsync again.
再试一次
That's scary.
真吓人
That was nothing.
那不算什么
Okay, same image.
好的 同样的图像
Yeah, there we go.
对 就是这样
Okay.
行
Finally booted, waiting to log in.
终于启动了 等着登录
Yeah, cool.
好吧 挺酷的
So then you see this.
然后你就能看到这个
You get to the login screen.
你到了登录界面
anybody know what next step is.
有人知道next step是什么
Yeah, so what was the story there?
对 那里有什么故事？
Do you know the story?
你知道这个故事吗？
Why is there a next?
为什么会有下一步？
Very close.
很接近了
Oh no, it's not going to be able to log in.
糟了 登不上了
Well, this is annoying.
真烦
Anyways, we can run it again in a second.
没关系 我们可以再试一次
So, but how could Steve Jobs create a company?
乔布斯是怎么创建公司的？
He created Apple, right?
他创立了苹果 是吧？
In a garage with Steve Wozniak.
和Steve Wozniak在车库里创建的
Yeah, he got fired from Apple. Doesn't that suck?
是的，他被苹果解雇了。 很恶心
You created this company
你创建了这家公司
built it from nothing in your garage
在自己的车库里从零打造了它
and then you get ousted and fired from the board.
然后你被排挤出董事会 甚至被开除了
So that's a whole story.
这就是整个故事
You can read about it.
你可以读到这个故事
I think there's probably movies about it, too, and stuff.
好像还被拍成了电影 还有其他的东西
So...
所以...
Ah, damn.
啊 真糟糕
Okay.
好吧
What it's doing now, basically there's
它现在基本上是在...
it's trying to do...
尝试...
This is my very stupid thing of doing screenshot comparison
这是我的笨办法 比较截图
because this has to run an emulator in a virtual environment
因为这需要在虚拟环境中运行模拟器
and then interact with it.
还要进行交互
Sometimes it gets stuck in a state like this
有时候会卡在这种状态
where it's waiting to see the login screen
等着登录界面出现
and it clearly can
会出现
but something is slightly different than what it expects
但稍微和预期不太一样
and it just hangs here.
结果就卡在这里了
So anyways, we can try that again.
所以 我们再试一次吧
It should take roughly about 12 or 13.
应该需要 12 或 13 秒
We should be able to see some stuff.
应该能看到些东西
Anyways, okay,
总之 好的
so yeah, so this was
所以 这就是
so the story was Steve Jobs left, created this company called Next,
史蒂夫·乔布斯离开苹果后 创立了 Next 公司
N-E-X-T
Next
which created this computer called the Next Step,
这家公司开发了一台名为 Next Step 的计算机
which was, I think, hardware and software
包括硬件和软件
which included a new, brand new operating system.
其中包含了一个全新的操作系统
And eventually that company was bought by Apple
后来这家公司被苹果收购了
so Steve Jobs came back to Apple
所以史蒂夫·乔布斯回到了苹果
and then ran the whole thing until he didn't anymore.
然后一直掌管着苹果 直到他不再掌管
And...
接着...
And what's fascinating
最有趣的是
and why what we'll get into here is
我们将要探讨的是
basically your goal is you need to pop this software through this interface.
你的目标是通过这个接口攻击这个软件
So you have to pop software that's running on the Next OS.
所以你需要攻击运行在 Next 操作系统上的这个软件
I think it's Next.
我觉得是 Next
I can't remember the exact version.
我记不清具体的版本了
We'll see it in a second.
我们一会儿就会看到
And specifically, the software that it's running
具体来说 运行的软件是
is the original World Wide Web browser
是最早的www浏览器
that Tim Berners-Lee wrote in 1993.
这是蒂姆·伯纳斯 - 李在 1993 年编写的
or 1994, which is the original.
还是1994 年， 最初的版本
And I'll show you the screenshot.
我来展示一下截图
It's actually running.
它正在运行
Actually, maybe I can show you ...
或许我可以展示
Yeah, I can.
可以
Okay, there's definitely a PNG in here
好的 这里确实有一个 PNG 文件
but one of them, let's talk.
我们来谈谈其中一个吧
Yeah, so what you eventually see is something like this.
最终你会看到这样的
So you see, and you can actually like play with this
你看 你可以实际操作一下
and run this stuff in an emulator.
在模拟器中运行这些东西
It's actually really cool because you can
真的很酷 因为你可以
if you use a Mac
如果你用的是 Mac
you can see that like the stuff that they still have there
你可以看到 有些东西
is still interaction paradigms that exist today.
至今仍在使用
So there's the www app.
有一个 www 应用
And then you'll notice in this is slash me.
然后你会发现这里有个 /me
So before, like, cause it wasn't multi-user systems
以前还没有多用户系统
there was just slash me.
当时只有 /me 这样的目录
/me/flag That is your goal to get that file.
/me/flag 就是目标文件
And eventually I think that other, let's see
后来我觉得还有其他的东西 让我看看
where's the other PNG.
其他 PNG 文件在哪
Ready.
准备好了
Good.
很好
Yeah.
嗯
So this is the.
所以这就是
Yeah, the World Wide Web app that's running here.
这里是运行的www应用
This is where it says overview of the web.
这里是对万维网的简要介绍
This is that that's running.
这就是正在运行的应用
So your goal is to pop this World Wide Web app through just giving it a URL
所以你的目标是通过提供一个 URL 来攻击这个万维网应用
and you'll be able to see how it gets through there.
你马上会知道如何实现
And to make things easier, of course, well
为了降低难度，当然
maybe not of course
也不一定降低了
if you've Maybe you're not used to things being easier.
如果你不太习惯事情变得简单
There's a tar file with the exact source code.
这里有一个包含源代码的 tar 文件
So you can read through the source code
因此你可以阅读源代码
figure out what's happening there.
搞清楚那里发生了什么
You can also copy everything in opt www.
你也可以把/opt/www 目录下的所有内容都复制过来
Is everything that's in there that you need to run this
那里有你需要运行这个的所有东西
So there's...
所以这里有...
This is like the disk drive that's actually running the next OS
可以说这个磁盘里面运行着NeXT操作系统
that has everything on it.
有这个系统的所有东西
I can't remember what these bins are.
我不记得这些 bin 文件是什么了
I think these are different OS boots or something like that.
我觉得这些是不同的操作系统启动文件之类的
And I have instructions of how you should be able to run this as a user on the desktop.
我有如何用桌面用户运行这个的说明
The current problem is that I think this...
目前的问题是 我觉得这个...
So previous is the name of this emulator.
所以这个模拟器的名字叫 previous
And I think previous is...
我记得previous……
having problems with the X that's running in your desktop container
与你机器上容器里运行的X，交互时有问题
but I'm trying to figure out a better way to do this.
但我正在找更好的解决方法
So you can actually like see what's going on when you run this easier.
这样你运行时就能更清楚地看到发生了什么
So this will launch tonight, later tonight
今晚稍后会启动
I guess I didn't set that up.
我还没设置好
And then, so what we'll do is
接下来 我们会
this will be a new module of like real world CTF challenges
它将是一个新的模块 包含真实的 CTF 挑战
and you'll have the whole rest of the semester to do that.
你有整个学期剩余的时间来完成这些挑战
So there'll just be a few to kind of not a ton
所以只有几个 不会太多
I won't like throw 10 at you at the last minute
不会在最后一刻一口气给你 10 个任务
but the idea is like actually apply what you learned to real world stuff.
重点是把学到的东西用到实际中
The other thing I'll say
还有一点我要说
because these are CTF challenges, there are write-ups where you can go look
因为这些是 CTF 挑战 所以能查到详细的writeup
and read exactly how to do this.
并了解具体的解决方法
I encourage you not to do that.
我不建议你们这么做
I can't prevent you from doing that.
我无法阻止你们
So, you know, use your good judgment and all that stuff
所以 要多用用自己的判断力 懂的都懂
and please don't do that unless you absolutely need to,
除非万不得已 否则不要这么做
in which case, whatever
实在需要就随你们了
I kind of don't care.
我其实不太在乎
This is, my goal is to point you at stuff to like, pop and study
我的目标是给你们推荐一些东西 你们可以去探索和学习
and that's the important part.
这才是关键的部分
Questions?
有问题吗？
Yeah.
说吧
Nope.
没有
This is not using QEMU.
这个没用 QEMU
It's using a custom.
它用的是自定义的
I don't know.
我不知道
I didn't write it
不是我写的
but this is an emulator for the Next OS specifically
但这是专门为 Next OS 设计的模拟器
and I think it's
我觉得这是
I think the architecture is some Motorola something something.
我觉得架构是摩托罗拉的
Yeah, so you don't have any nice
没错 你没有什么好的
it's not like QEMU
不像 QEMU 那样
you don't have any nice stuff you have
你没有其他好东西
but I will say once you get this environment to boot
但一旦这个环境启动了
you can poke around and do stuff.
你就可以随便看看 做点事
See, I don't know why this didn't work either
我也不明白为什么这个失败了
but now I'm upset because this was working.
但现在我很难受 因为它之前是没问题的
Anyways, I'll fix it.
不管怎样 我会修好的
It'll work.
它肯定能行
It worked for an entire CTF
它在 CTF 比赛中没出问题
so it definitely does work
所以肯定行
but This was done six years ago, so this stuff kind of breaks
但这是六年前做的 所以有些问题
and then you have to update it.
然后需要更新一下
If anybody saw, this front-end code that you talked to
如果有人看过 你与之交互的前端代码
is all Python 2 as well.
全是 Python 2
So we're living in the past.
现在都过时了
This is a well way in the past.
这已经非常过时了
Cool.
好的
Any other questions?
还有其他问题吗？
All right.
好吧
Yeah, curse of the demo in true Apple fashion.
典型的苹果风格 演示时总是出问题
Very, very true.
确实没错
I swear this was working at one point.
我保证这东西之前还能用
I did get screenshots.
我截了图
It got to the point where it was loading the ...
它那时已经在加载 ...
Actually, what's very funny
其实 有趣的是
does anybody know the first website?
有人知道第一个网站是什么吗？
You think the web just sprung out of existence?
你以为网站是一下子就有的吗？
No.
不
Ah, info.
啊 信息
Yeah.
好
So this was the first website, info.cern.ch.
这就是第一个网站 info.cern.ch
I mean, anybody know why the web was created?
有人知道为什么要创建互联网吗？
You use it every single day.
你们每天都在用
You never thought where did this come from?
没想过 这东西是从哪儿来的？
Wasn't it an alternative form of like, Communication for the military.
难道它不是一种军事通讯的替代形式？
No, you're thinking of the internet and the ARPANET.
不是 你说的是互联网和阿帕网
So the ARPANET is the internet, right?
阿帕网就是互联网前身
That's how packets move around, TCP, IP, all of that.
这就是数据包的传输方式 TCP、IP 等
But before the web
但在网站出现之前
you still had what?
你们还有哪些东西？
What's not web?
有哪些不是web的服务？
Mail.
电子邮件
Yeah, mail, email, SMTP, POP, IMAP.
对 电子邮件、SMTP、POP、IMAP
What else?
还有什么？
Telnet.
What was it?
什么？
Telnet, yep.
Telnet 对
What else?
还有呢？
How'd you move files around?
你们怎么传输文件的？
FTP predates the web.
FTP 比web还早
Use groups, I think
用群组吧 我觉得
but I don't really
但我不太确定
that's way predates my time.
那早在我那个年代之前了
I don't quite understand how they actually function
我不太明白它们是怎么运作的
but people have got like BBSs and all kinds of stuff.
但人们已经有 BBS 和各种各样的东西了
so the web, right?
所以 web
The web is like web browser plus HTML plus the concept of hyperlinks.
web就像是web浏览器加上超文本标记语言（HTML）和超链接的概念
So you can click on a document to go to the next document.
你可以点击一个文档转到下一个文档
These were things that were kind of in the air at the time.
这些想法在当时都很流行
People were proposing this like, wow
人们提出这个想法时 都觉得太棒了
wouldn't it be crazy if you like had a document on your computer
如果你的电脑上有文档
and then that document had links to other documents
这些文档又链接到其他文档
and those documents had links to other documents.
这些文档又链接到更多文档
And what Tim Berners-Lee was a researcher who was working at CERN.
蒂姆·伯纳斯 - 李是欧洲核子研究组织的研究员
So what does CERN do?
那么 欧洲核子研究组织是做什么的？
Yeah, the particle accelerator.
对 就是粒子加速器
I just think of like big circle, right?
我总是想到一个大环
So they like spin stuff around and hit things
他们喜欢让粒子旋转然后互相撞击
and I don't know
具体的我也不太清楚
do stuff that I don't, whatever, whatever they do
做一些我不知道的实验
the physicists do when they hit things at high speeds.
物理学家做的一些对高速撞击的记录计算
But he was there and you have this problem at CERN
他在那里时，欧洲核子研究组织面临这个问题
that you had too many people coming and leaving all the time.
人员流动非常频繁
So you didn't know who was there or where they were.
所以你根本不知道谁在哪里
And so what he really wanted was a better directory for CERN.
所以他真正想要的是一个更好的 CERN 人员目录
Like who does what kind of research
比如谁在做哪方面的研究
and what's their phone number
以及他们的电话号码是多少
and office number that you can go contact them.
以及可以联系他们的办公室电话
So he created the worldwide web browser using a next step physical machine
因此他用 NextStep 系统的机器，创建了web浏览器
that's what he was developing on, to create HTTP,
他用的这台机器做开发，创建了 HTTP（超文本传输协议）
the communication protocol of requesting an hypertext document,
这是一种请求超文本文档的通信协议
HTML, and like URIs and URLs
超文本标记语言（HTML）、统一资源标识符（URI）和统一资源定位符（URL）
and defining that whole concept.
并定义了整个概念
So he created that in
他创建了这些
I believe it was, let's see
我记得是在
I believe it was like 92
我记得是 1992 年
Let's see, the birth of the web. 1989.
看一下， web诞生的年份  1989 年
Interesting, that seems a little early.
有趣 这似乎有点早
But look, you can see, look at this picture.
但是看看这张图片
Anybody recognize this?
有人认出这个了吗？
This is like exactly what we were just looking at of this,
这正是我们刚才看到的
the next cube in the upper right.
右上角的NeXT立方体
You have the World Wide Web thing here.
这里是www的一些东西
This is 100% like the same thing.
这完全一样
Yeah, here's the...
是的 这里就是……
And then let's go back
然后我们回来……
and then browse the first website.
浏览一下首个网站
So this was the first website of like, because
所以这就是第一个网站
anyways the whole reason I started talking about this is like
我之所以提到这个是因为……
you think of like now
你现在会想到
you open up a browser
你打开浏览器
where do you want it to take you?
你希望它带你去哪里？
Like your homepage, but the internet didn't
大概是主页 但当时互联网还没...
there wasn't a, sorry, the internet existed
当时有互联网
but there wasn't a web.
但还没有网站
So what is the
那么问题来了
where do you send people?
人们都上网看什么
So you had to have a site
所以需要一个引导网站
And that was this info.cern.ch.
这个网站就是 info.cern.ch
Although this version I have, for some reason
这个版本不知为何
tries to talk to this cernvax.cern.ch.
总是尝试与 cernvax.cern.ch 通信
And it tries to connect to it every time.
每次都会尝试连接
And if it can't get the DNS address to talk to it
如果获取不到 DNS 地址
it pops up a little alert dialog that you have to click OK for.
会弹出一个警告对话框 需要点击确定
So I'm trying to...
所以我尝试……
Anyways, the thing I was debugging is that
总之 我在调试时
running my own DNS server to respond and be like
运行自己的 DNS 服务器来响应
this is at 127.0.0.1
告诉它地址在 127.0.0.1
Just, like, fetch something and go away.
获取点东西 然后别弹窗
And...
然后...
Anyways, to make that go away.
总之 想办法不让他弹窗
Maybe I should just figure out how to click on it
或许我该弄清怎么点击它
but I don't like the idea of clicking on things.
但我不是很喜欢点击东西
It's way more brittle than typing things.
这比打字麻烦多了
So, anyways.
所以 总之
Okay, that was a long diversion
好吧 离题了
but this is the history of the web.
但这就是web的历史
Yeah, get the code.
对 获取代码
Yeah, of the www browser.
对 www 浏览器的代码
So, yeah.
是的 就是这样
So this is the exact...
这就是……
And the other interesting thing
还有一个有趣的是
as you poke around with it
使用它的时候
you can actually browse the internet.
你可以用它浏览网页
It looks really weird because the thing doesn't recognize JavaScript.
看起来很奇怪 因为它不识别 JavaScript
So you can see all the JavaScript.
会显示 js代码
You can actually load real websites
你能访问真实的网站
into this browser from like the early 90s.
用这个90 年代初的浏览器
Kind of.
有点儿
Yeah, and the other super important thing in here is this editor part.
是的 另一个非常重要的部分是这个编辑器
So actually the vision of the web was a WYSIWYG
实际上 Web的愿景是WYSIWYG
like what you see is what you get, editor.
即，所见即所得的编辑器
So you can not only browse websites
因此 你不仅可以浏览网站
but also edit them through the browser
还能通过浏览器编辑它们
and save them and serialize the HTML back to the server.
并保存编辑内容 将 HTML 数据传回服务器
That was like the original concept.
这是最初的设想
Part of the problem though, at least historically is that
然而，问题在于，至少是当时的问题
this browser was so tied to Next Step
这个浏览器与 NextStep 系统紧密耦合
because it only ran there, that...
因为只能在那个系统上运行
They didn't have enough
它们缺乏足够的
or there wasn't enough market share that it didn't spread
或者因为市场太小 没能普及开来
but other people used the protocols
但其他人使用这些协议
and wrote web servers and different browsers.
开发了web服务器和各种浏览器
So Mosaic was the first browser that was super popular.
Mosaic 是第一个特别流行的浏览器
And then you had Netscape and all this other stuff,
接着有 Netscape 和其他各种产品
Internet Explorer, everything there.
IE等
So anyways, I really like this.
总之 我真的很喜欢这东西
I think this is a cool first challenge
用它做第一题，很棒
because A you'll have to read real source code to find this bug.
因为首先你得阅读真实源代码，才能找到这个 bug
And it's easier because you don't have to decompile this Motorola,whatever.
并且它简单 因为不必反编译这个 Motorola xxx
I mean, maybe you actually will need to to figure out offsets and whatnot
你可能需要确定些偏移量之类的
but you can have the source code to read through
但你能读到源代码
which is exactly the problem we're going to.
这正是我们要解决的问题
You have the system
当你有系统
you have source code
有源代码
you have the binary.
有二进制文件
How do you actually try to find the bugs and vulnerabilities there?
你该如何找到其中的安全漏洞？
Cool.
酷
All right.
好吧
And then writing shell code for another language is fun
还有给另一种语言写 shellcode 很有趣
especially because this is in the 90s, so Like, they're like, ASLR
特别是在 90 年代 ASLR？
that doesn't even make that's not even a word yet.
那时候听都没听过
And like, executable stack what do you mean?
还有可执行栈 什么意思？
All memory is readable, writable, and executable.
所有内存都可读、可写、可执行
Like, this is just concepts that don't make sense.
这些保护机制概念都没道理
So the actual exploitation is easy.
所以漏洞利用简单
It's just like fitting this model of what you know how to do
就像把你的技能和知识
into a new system
应用在一个新系统上
is, I think, interesting and fun.
我觉得挺有趣 也很好玩
Yeah, so 93 is when it was released to the public.
是的 93 年它对公众发布了
That's why I have 93 in there.
所以我在里面加了 93
Cool.
酷
Any other questions, historical or otherwise?
还有其他问题吗？历史或其他方面的
All right, this still didn't work, did it?
好吧 这还是没成功 对吧？
Oh, it did.
噢 成功了
Oh, look at that.
哦 瞧
So you talk long enough and eventually
只要讲得足够久，最终
wait what am I doing?
等等 我在做什么？
Why am I in there multiple times?
为啥我反复出现？
What's going on here?
这是怎么回事？
Okay.
行
And let's see, 19.
来看看 截图19
Yeah, so there's that alert that I was talking about.
这就是我之前说的那个警告
That's super annoying.
它很烦
But it did, no, let's see, 13.
但 我们来看看 截图13
Yeah, so it is able to start
对 它可以启动了
oh this is the app, worldwideweb.app.
哦 这是 worldwideweb.app 应用
And just like, so if you use a Mac
如果你用 Mac
everything that you have in applications is actually called like a .app
应用文件夹里的所有内容其实都是 .app 文件
and they're not an executable
它们不是可执行的
it's a directory with a specific structure.
而是一个有着特定结构的文件夹
The structure is almost the same now.
和现在的结构差不多
And does anybody do any Mac OS, like user space coding,
有人在 Mac OS 上做过用户空间编程吗
like code apps or something?
比如写应用之类的？
Everybody's shaking their head.
大家都在摇头
I guess that's why you're taking this class.
我想这就是你们选这门课的原因
Anyways, all of the, almost all of the, not internal
总之 几乎所有 非系统内部
but like the system level stuff begins with capital NS.
而是系统级别的内容，都以大写的 NS 开头
And that stands for next step.
NS 代表 NextStep
So like there's NS string is like
NS 字符串就是这样
I think it's like cocoa or whatever their objective C.
感觉像 cocoa 或 Objective-C
like all of their frameworks start with ...
他们的框架开头都是...
and almost everything starts with NS
几乎所有的都以 NS 开头
because it comes all the way from next step
因为这都源自 NextStep
and they've like carried that all the way through.
他们一直沿用至今
So you can see things like that.
所以你会看到类似的东西
Kind of,
有点像
yeah, yeah, exactly.
是的 是的 完全正确
Like kind of like the NT kernel, but basically
有点像 NT 内核 但基本上
but the crazy thing for me is it came from this other company that they acquired
但最让我惊讶的是 这东西来自他们收购的公司
and then like they threw out their operating system that they had at the time
然后他们把当时自己的操作系统扔了
and like use this.
改用了这个
Cool, okay, so I think this will be really fun
酷 我觉得这会非常有趣
Yeah, and there's also an exit patch if you get stuck.
对 如果你卡住了 还有退出补丁
Okay.
好的
So enough about, yeah
不说这个了
this does not work yet
这个还不能用
but it will eventually.
但最终会能用的
Okay, so enough about this.
好吧 不聊这个了
What time is it, five?
现在几点了？五点了吗？
All right, let me set a timer.
好的 我来设个定时器
Set a timer for 25 minutes, please.
请设个 25 分钟的定时器
Okay.
好的
All right, now we're going to do
好的 现在我们来
turn our attention to the operating system.
注意力转向操作系统
So I talked a lot last week about how to approach a target, right,
上周我详细讲了如何接近目标 对吧？
or how to even select a target, so the first step of approaching a target.
或者说如何选择目标 这是接近目标的第一步
Now that we've chosen a target
既然选定了目标
we want to do reconnaissance on that target.
我们需要对这个目标进行侦察
Why is reconnaissance important?
为什么侦察如此重要？
To understand attack vectors
为了了解攻击途径
which is why is that important.
这就是为什么这很重要
Say it again.
再说一遍
Yeah, I would say that how do you know
嗯 怎么判断呢
it's more about vulnerabilities, right?
主要是漏洞 对吧？
So how can I influence the application by knowing what input I can feed in
了解了可输入内容后 我该如何影响这个应用
what are the attack factors, right?
以及攻击途径有哪些 对吧？
So understanding the system, super important.
所以 了解系统非常重要
So we're going to dig in today
所以今天我们深入探讨一下
and I have some fun ideas planned
我准备了一些有趣的点子
that we're going to read a lot of source code
我们会读很多源代码
and dig in through this beast.
并深入这个系统
So, okay, I guess before I start
在我开始之前
I meant to contact some of my friends who work at Apple.
我打算联系一些在苹果工作的朋友
I don't actually know how to pronounce.
我其实不知道该怎么读
I don't know if it's like X-NU.
我不确定是不是读作 X-new
I don't think anyone does that
我觉得没有人这么读
but I always say X-N-U
但我一直读 X-N-U
but I don't know how people pronounce this
但我不知道大家怎么读
so I apologize in advance if
所以我提前道个歉
you've learned something from me that people are like, what an idiot.
万一你学了我的，别人说你
Why would you say things like that?
“说的什么玩意这是”
So X-N-U.
所以 X-N-U
It stands for X is Not Unix, like a classic old school acronym.
它代表 X 不是 Unix ，一个经典的老式缩写
And it is...
而且 它就是……
Like we said, originally developed for Next Step.
正如我们所说 最初是为 Next Step 开发的
So this is what's really cool.
所以 这才是最酷的地方
You're going to be popping a user space application for the Next Step OS.
后面会攻击一个 NextStep 操作系统上的用户空间程序
Well, that would be a fun follow-on challenge.
想到一个有趣的后续挑战
Pop a kernel, find some bug in the kernel and pop that.
攻击内核 找到内核中的漏洞并利用它
That could be a cool challenge.
那会是一个很酷的挑战
All right.
好的
So this ties in really nicely
这一切都紧密相连
like we said that.
正如我们所说
So the stuff that you are seeing
你看到的内容
You will see how it's been carried forward.
你会看到它是如何传承的
XNU is also the kernel.
XNU 也是内核
There's this very confusing thing
有件挺让人困惑的事
that the operating system is called Darwin in Mac land
在 Mac 系统中 操作系统叫 Darwin
but the kernel is XNU
但内核是 XNU
and the kernel is also used on almost all Apple stuff, so
而且内核也被用于几乎所有苹果设备
Macs, iPhones, tablets, probably HomePods too, I would assume
Mac、iPhone、平板电脑 可能还有 HomePod
and every device that I think is slightly smart.
以及我认为稍微智能的设备
I don't know about the headphones and stuff
耳机那块我不太清楚
because they have something on there.
因为里面有些东西
There's some chip in there, the H-something.
里面有个 H开头的芯片
I don't know exactly what's in there.
具体是什么我也不清楚
There's also the other crazy thing.
还有个更疯狂的
Who actually has a Mac?
谁有 Mac ？
First question.
第一个问题
Two?  I see two in this room.
两个？我在这儿看到两个
Is there any more?
还有没有？
You're all Linux people or Windows people?
你们用的是 Linux 还是 Windows？
Wow, okay.
哇 行
That'll make my next thing sad.
那我的下一件事就尴尬了
Anyways,
不管怎样
the...
这……
This guy, $90 dongle, USB-C to power HDMI and USB-A adapter.
这个 $90 的 USB-C 转 HDMI 和 USB-A 适配器
I bought this for the thing
我买这个是为了
because this was before they had the HDMI adapters built in
因为在那之前还没有内置的 HDMI 适配器
which is a very nice feature.
这真是个很棒的功能
But before you had that
但在那之前
you had to have a dongle like this.
你得用这样一个转接头
I plugged it in and the computer said
我插上后 电脑提示
do you want to update the firmware of your dongle?
“要更新转接头的固件吗？”
And of course, as a security person, I said yes.
当然 作为安全人员 我选了“是”
But then my second thought as a security person is
但作为安全人员 我立刻想
why in the world is there software running on this device?
这设备上怎么会有软件运行？
So there is something running on here that maybe you can hack.
所以这里运行着些东西 可能能被黑
I have absolutely no idea.
我完全不清楚
But that would be a very interesting attack surface of
但这将是一个很有趣的攻击面
like, popping the dongle
比如攻击这个转接头
through either HDMI input or USB input or something like that.
通过 HDMI 输入或 USB 输入之类的
I assume it's got to be very simple.
我觉得它应该很简单
Like, it cannot be that complicated of, like
它不可能太复杂
it's just got to shunt things around for, like
它只是需要转发数据
If you have to update it
既然需要更新
there must have been some bug that they needed to fix.
肯定有需要修复的错误
Hopefully it was not a security bug
希望不是安全漏洞
but I have no idea.
但我也不知道
But anyways, that would be super cool if anybody could do that.
但不管怎样 如果有人能做到就太酷了
Maybe, but it should just pass through, right?
也许吧 但它应该只是简单通过 对吗？
Because, like, you have USB.
因为 你有 USB 接口
I have, okay, so.
我有 所以呢
Yeah, but, like.
是啊 不过
Yeah.
嗯
Like, yeah, here's, like, a USB-A to USB-C adapter.
这是个 USB-A 转 USB-C 的转换器
Like, I would be shocked
我会感到很震惊
if there's, like complex software running on here that needs updates
如果这里，运行着需要更新的复杂程序
or that there was even any way to update whatever's on here.
甚至，竟然有方法更新这里的东西
It's, like, a $5 thing, like, throw it away, I guess.
这东西也就几美元 干脆扔了算了
Anyways, also the displays.
还有 显示器
So the, like, Mac Studio and the other Apple displays, like
像 Mac Studio 还有其他 Apple 显示器
when you plug them in
一插上电脑
you can also update the firmware, like
你还能更新上面的固件
the stuff that's running on there.
运行在上面的系统
I don't know if that's a pared-down version of XNU, but...
不确定这是否是 XNU 的简化版 不过……
Basically, they've shown that almost every device they use
他们几乎所有的设备
has XNU as the kernel
都用了 XNU 内核
which is pretty cool.
真的挺酷的
It was initially released in 1996
它在1996 年首次发布
which is kind of cool.
还挺酷的
It's very, very old.
算得上非常老了
The other crazy thing is it was open source in 2000.
另一件疯狂的事 它在 2000 年开源了
And I think I lied a little bit at the beginning of the class
我想我在课上说错了一点
of why it's open source.
关于它为什么开源的原因
I thought it was because it came from the
我以为是因为它来源于
as we'll see, used BSD stuff and this other mach kernel.
它使用了 BSD 组件和mach微内核
But I don't think those were copy left operating systems.
但我不认为那些是 copyleft 操作系统
they could have just completely used them and never done anything
他们完全可以，不做任何改动地，使用这些系统
but apparently there's this apple public source license
但显然有一个苹果公共源代码许可证
that they license everything under
他们所有的东西都在这个许可下发布
and um well that's not my password that'd be weird password
而且 那不是我的密码 太奇怪了
and uh it is a i'm not a lawyer
而且 我不是律师
so please for the love of god don't like take anything i say  to court or whatever
所以拜托，上法庭之类的，别用我的这些话
But this is a verified open source license.
但这确实是一个经过验证的开源许可
I don't know the differences between this and other licenses
我不知道这个许可和其他许可有什么区别
but it's kind of crazy that they just decided to open source their kernel.
但他们决定开源他们的内核，这确实有点疯狂
Some theories that I read people hypothesize is that like at the time
我读到的一些理论认为 当时
they had such little market share that that was a way
他们的市场份额非常小，这样可以
plus they were replacing their old OS kernel
另外他们还在用 Next Step 的新 XNU 内核
with this new XNU stuff from Next Step.
替换旧的操作系统内核
And so they wanted to try to convince people that it was more reliable
他们想靠这个，说服大家这更可靠
because they could go read the source.
因为人们可以阅读源代码
Maybe it was like a marketing ploy
也许这是一种营销策略
because then you wouldn't be tied into their stuff
这样你就不会被绑定在他们的系统上
and you could just take it.
你可以直接使用
I have absolutely no idea.
我完全不知道
But yeah, it's pretty crazy that they still do this
但确实很疯狂 他们至今还在这么做
because I guess at any point they could just not do this
因为他们随时可以停止这么做
and they would be fine.
也不会有影响
They wouldn't be violating licenses.
他们不会违规
I don't know.
我不知道
It's crazy.
这真疯狂
Okay.
行
Cool.
挺好的
So XNU is crazy.
所以 XNU 真是太疯狂了
And I think I mentioned this before.
我想我之前提到过
Uh, it is a amalgamation of various components and parts
呃 它由各种组件组成
kind of glued together over the years and grown very organically.
这些组件粘在一起，多年来，形成了有机结合
I think that's natural of any operating system, right?
我认为任何操作系统都是这样 对吧？
They have to evolve over time.
它们必须随着时间演变
You don't just like sit down and design it from scratch
你不会一开始，就能从头设计它
but it is a
但它是一个……
we think of as like a hybrid kernel with a split personality
我们认为它是一个具有双重性格的混合内核
meaning there are two different worlds.
这意味着有两个不同的世界
There's the BSD world.
一个是 BSD 的世界
So there's a kernel.
所以有一个内核
that they basically took from a BSD 4.3, which actually
这个内核基本上取自 BSD 4.3
I think I already have an idea of the next real world thing
我认为我已经想好了，下一个要攻击的目标
is gonna be software that runs on BSD 4.3,
那将是运行在 BSD 4.3 上的软件
which is actually, again
这又是一个
another great connection to what we're doing and looking at history.
很好的结合了我们所学的和历史的例子
So this was released in 1986
这个版本发布于 1986 年
kind of giving you a timeline of where we are.
这有助于我们了解所处的时间线
A lot of things in BSD ended up in current kernels,
BSD 中的许多功能最终都集成到现代内核中
especially like the TCP IP stack.
尤其是 TCP/IP 栈
This was one of the first major implementations of the TCP IP stack that then got used
这是最早的 后来被广泛采用的 TCP/IP 栈实现之一
because BSD has a very permissive license.
因为 BSD 的许可证非常宽松
People just yanked it and used it in their OS kernels.
人们直接将其用在了自己的操作系统内核中
And the interesting thing is
有趣的是
so they started with this 4.3 BSD
他们从 4.3 BSD 开始
and BSD kind of kept evolving, right?
BSD 一直在发展 对吧？
But they, as we'll see
但正如我们看到的
because they had this like Frankenstein monster,
他们的这个像个弗兰克斯坦怪人一样，
this other part, they modified things
这部分进行了很多修改
but they kind of kept up and shared code with FreeBSD.
但他们算是跟上FreeBSD 并与之共享代码
So as FreeBSD evolved
因此 随着 FreeBSD 的发展
Apple would take some patches from FreeBSD
苹果会从 FreeBSD 获取一些补丁
and they would also ship patches back to and upstream them to FreeBSD from XNU.
还会将XNU中FreeBSD补丁回馈给FreeBSD
I don't know
我不知道
I think that's kind of interesting to look at, like, this,
我觉得这挺有趣的
like, weird co-evolution here.
一种奇怪的共同进化
Actually, the fun fact is during my sabbatical
有趣的是 在我休假期间
one of the bugs I found was the oldest bug
我发现的一个最老的漏洞
because it dated back to, I think, either 4.3, like, BSD kernel.
因为它可以追溯到 4.3 版的 BSD 内核
I was able to trace that that bug was actually still present here,
我追查到这个漏洞仍然存在
but it...
但...
I guess I shouldn't say this
我大概不该说这个
because it says how old I am
因为这暴露了我的年龄
but it's still not older than me.
但还是没有我年纪大
I wanted to find a bug that was older than I was
我想找一个比我还大的漏洞
and that was not it.
但它不是
It was very close, though.
不过很接近了
The other side is a mach kernel.
另一个是mach微内核
So the mach kernel was, again, created around the same time, 1985.
mach 是在 1985 年左右创建的
You can kind of see
你可以看出
especially if you read papers from this area
特别是如果你读过这方面的论文
or look at the research that's been done
或者看看相关的研究
you can kind of see that there was, like, this explosion of different, like
你能看出，此时涌现出了
operating system ideas
不同的操作系统理念
of like, oh, no this is how we should do a kernel
就像，应该这样制作内核
or this is how we should do a kernel.
不，这才是内核的制作方法
When was Linux released?
Linux 是什么时候发布的？
My Linux heads.
我的 Linux 粉丝们
You do this stuff all the time.
你们总用它
You don't know when it came out.
不知道它的发布时间？
History is important.
历史很重要
You're just making stuff up.
你们是在胡编乱造
Can somebody look?
有人能查一下吗？
79?
79？
The radio was in the 30s.
无线电是在 30 年代
Oh, my God. What?
天啊 什么？
91 年？
Thank you. Yes, 91.
谢谢 对 91 年
That makes sense because they had FTP and stuff and the internet.
这说得通 因为那时已经有 FTP 和互联网了
Like it can't have...
它不可能有……
Anyways.
总之
Okay.
好的
Around this time.
大约这个时候
So like in a similar timeframe, right?
差不多同一时期 对吧？
Late 80s, early 90s.
80 年代末 90 年代初
There's a lot of exploration and experimentation in this stuff.
当时对这个有很多探索和实验
And the cool thing was the mach kernel was developed at CMU.
最酷的是 mach是在卡内基梅隆大学开发的
So it was a research project.
所以 这是一个研究项目
This actually is...
这实际上是...
I can't remember who did it, but...
我不记得是谁做的 不过...
One of the Project Zero people, it was probably
可能是 Project Zero 的某个人
I don't know if it was Brandon while he was there, Brandon Azad or Ian Beer
不确定是 Brandon Azad 还是 Ian Beer
or maybe it was Ned
或者可能是 Ned
but they wrote a Project Zero blog post
但他们写了一篇 Project Zero 的博客文章
about exploiting bugs in the memory mapping and allocation in modern day XNU.
详细介绍了如何利用，现代 XNU 内存映射与分配的漏洞
And to understand the allocator
为了理解这个分配器
they went back to papers that were published in like the late 80s early 90s about mach
他们查阅了，80 年代末90 年代初发表的，关于mach的论文
because it still has those features today.
因为这些设计沿用至今
And so it actually helped him understand that system
通过阅读这些非常古老的论文
by reading these super old papers.
让他更好地理解了这个系统
This is also why history is important.
这也是为什么历史如此重要
You should know when things came from and how old they are.
你应该了解技术的起源和它的历史
Are they 100 years old or 30 years old?
是 100 年前的 还是 30 年前的？
34, 35, 36? 33
34 年、35 年、36 年？33 年
Okay.
好的
I was going the wrong direction.
我弄错方向了
And initially, so the mach kernel
一开始 mach内核
and this was a big fight, just like...
有一个激烈冲突，就像
I hoped people would argue about the RISC versus CISC debate in the 90s.
我希望人们能像 90 年代那样争论 RISC 和 CISC
Similar debates in operating system kernels were
操作系统内核中的类似争论是
monolithic kernels versus microkernels.
单内核vs微内核
So what's the difference?
那么 它们有什么区别？
Somebody tell me.
有人告诉我吗？
Yeah, so the idea is like monolithic kernel, big kernel, lots of stuff
对 单内核就是 内核大 功能多
like everything's in
所有功能都在一起
you can think of it as one address space.
你可以认为它在同一个地址空间内
The real downside is
缺点是
basically one failure mode.
基本上只要一个错误
So any seg fault or something in any kernel code
内核代码中任何段错误之类的
the entire kernel crashes.
都会导致整个内核崩溃
Also from a vulnerability perspective, right?
从安全漏洞的角度来看 也一样
You pop the kernel
一旦你攻破了内核
you own everything and it doesn't, nothing else matters.
你就掌控了一切 其他都不重要了
However, with a microkernel design
然而 采用微内核设计
the idea was separate the functionality of the kernel into little pieces
它将内核功能分解成小部分
and that way an individual piece could crash
这样 即使某一部分崩溃
and that would be fine. The rest of the operating system would still survive and go on.
问题也不大，其余部分依然可以继续运行
I guess you have to restart that part
我想你必须重启那部分
and that's why you have all these debates over like
所以会争论
is that actually useful?
这到底有没有用？
But then you have this mechanism of like, okay
但后来有了这种机制
but you need to talk to other things.
你需要与其它部分通信
And so how do you do that in an efficient manner?
那你如何高效实现呢？
Like in a mono... what does it say monolithic kernel
在单内核中
how would you call functionality from another component
如何调用其他组件的功能？
yeah just a function call
对 就是函数调用
right you just call
对 你直接调用
and then boom you're there get the code code back
然后 你就到需要的代码了
you can call any function anywhere in the kernel it's great um
你可以在代码中，调用内核中的任何函数 很方便
but you can have problems
但你可能会遇到问题
and you can that can cause massive problems so um
这可能会导致严重的问题
That's where mach came from was this idea of
在mach 出现时，有这么一个想法
how do we design a microkernel with message passing
如何设计带有消息传递的微内核
and the message passing is very efficient
并且消息传递要非常高效
because that's the downside if you have message passing components.
因为这是用消息传递组件的缺点
The cool thing is
酷的是
so which design won out in the operating system wars?
那么在操作系统大战中 哪种设计胜出了？
Yeah, Linux is monolithic, Windows is monolithic
是的 Linux 是单内核 Windows 也是单内核
XMU is actually monolithic
XMU 实际上是单内核的
even though it has this stuff that like
尽管它有类似微内核的特性
it's kind of microkernel.
有点像微内核
And you can actually see the trend of like
你可以看到这种趋势
a lot of operating systems
许多操作系统
are trying to move more stuff into user space
都在尝试将更多功能移到用户空间
or like give reduce the need for companies or users to write kernel extensions
尽量让用户，无需编写内核扩展
because that gets now part of your
因为这成了
this is exactly the CloudStrike problem, if anybody remembers, right?
这就是 CloudStrike 问题 如果还有人记得的话 对吧？
There's a kernel extension that had a bug that blue screened the computer on every boot
有个内核扩展有漏洞，能让电脑每次启动时蓝屏
Whereas if they had APIs of doing what they wanted
但如果让用户使用内核API实现所需功能
that user space process would crash
那么用户进程可能崩溃
and the rest of the kernel would be fine.
但内核的其他部分，不会有事
So you can see that.
所以你看
So monolithic kernels won out
所以 单内核当时胜出
probably at the time, I would say, due to performance.
主要是因为性能优势
Nobody wants to take a 10%, 20% performance hit on stuff.
没人希望性能下降 10% 到 20%
You're just like, hey, your kernel crashed. Fix your stupid kernel bug
一般就 “嘿，你内核崩了，赶紧修一下bug”
which is what they did over the years.
这正是内核开发者一直做的
It became more resilient.
这让内核变得更健壮了
But...
但是...
This idea wasn't dead
这个想法没有消亡
and this is what I think is super important
这正是我认为很重要的一点
of looking at these things historically,
从历史角度看
of being like, well
也就是说
they did all this research into microkernels.
他们对微内核进行了大量研究
Was this wasted?
这些研究是浪费了吗
The idea is no.
不是的
So what's a modern piece of software
有哪些现代软件
that I guarantee you 80% of this room uses every day
我敢保证在座的 80% 每天都用到
that has a microkernel-like design?
它们有类似微内核的设计
Yeah, what browser?
什么浏览器？
Chrome.
Yes, Chrome, for security reasons, has a ton of different sandboxes.
没错 Chrome 为了安全 设计了多种沙箱
You have the render in it.
渲染也在其中
They created a model
他们创建了一个模型
where they separated each thing into a different process, right?
将每个部分隔离在不同的进程中 对吧？
Just like a microkernel has separate components running in isolated spaces.
就像微内核将不同组件运行在隔离的空间中
Chrome used different processes to do that same isolation
Chrome 也通过不同的进程来实现这种隔离
but they need a mechanism to talk to each other.
但它们需要一种机制来互相通信
So they had to create mechanisms to do this.
因此 他们创建了相应机制实现这个
And so you could see that
你可以把这个
as like those ideas or the evolution of the microkernel design philosophy
看做微内核设计理念
influencing modern day software that you use all the time.
影响着我们日常使用的软件
Oh, and I highlighted message passing
哦 我还特别标注了消息传递
because this will technology gods willing that
因为如果一切顺利的话
this will be our first thing
这将是我们的首个目标
that we'll actually get to play with the message passing part of mach
我们会玩一玩mach的消息传递部分
and be able to use it to talk to different
用它与其他组件通信
use it to really understand the IPC design there.
用它来深入理解mach的进程间通信设计
This is kind of a weird thing that I only include here.
有个奇怪的事，我只在这里提了
So they initially took this like version 2.5 of mach for the original XNU with Nextstep.
他们最初在NextStep的XNU， 用的 2.5 版本的 mach
Then when they merged it in
他们将其合并进去时
there's apparently this open source foundation mach kernel OS FMK.
有一个名为 OSFMK 的开源 mach 内核操作系统
The only reason why I'm talking about this is
我之所以提到这个
because this is the directory you are looking for
因为这就是你要找的目录
when you're looking for mach stuff.
当你查找 mach 相关内容时
And I always forget that.
我总是忘了这一点
And I always never remember what the heck this thing means.
我总忘这个OSFMK是什么意思
And I just like create acronyms in my head of like
我总爱在脑袋里编一些缩写
something make is always what I think of because of the MK
总让我想起来xxx制造，因为这个mk
but it's not
但其实不是
it's the mach kernel.
mk 是 mach 内核
So yeah, they, which includes parts of like mach three
它包括了部分 mach 3
and some forks and all of their stuff.
和一些fork的，和之类的内容
Anyways, it kind of was a conglomeration of everything.
总之 算是一个大杂烩
So.
所以
Just like every operating system
就像每个操作系统一样
this is taken from Wikipedia
这是从维基百科摘来的
so I apologize for the very terrible graphic
所以 抱歉 这张图很烂
that I didn't create So I guess it's either my fault or not my fault
它不是我做的，我猜，这是也不是我的错
depending on how you look at it.
这看你怎么想了
So like every kernel
就像每个内核一样
there is a differentiation between user mode and user space and the kernel itself.
用户空间和内核之间有区别
I mean, simple question
问一个简单问题
why do we have that differentiation?
为什么要有区别？
For task, what's a task?
为了任务 什么是任务？
Yeah, so every, like, the operating system, like,
是的，操作系统
the goal of the operating system in the kernel, right
操作系统内核的目的是
is to make sure that user space programs can do whatever they need to do
确保用户空间程序，能实现他们想做的
without harming each other
而且不会互相干扰
and dealing with access to hardware and everything because you, I mean
并处理硬件访问等所有事务。
back in the DOS days
在 DOS 时代
if I remember correctly
如果我没记错的话
each application just used whatever memory it needed
应用可以直接用他们所需的内存
had full access to everything.
并且可以访问所有资源
And so you just couldn't run two applications at once.
所以你不能同时运行两个应用程序
This is like, I don't know
这就像 我不知道
maybe to people that think
可能对于那些
that radio was invented in the 70s
认为收音机是在 70 年代发明的人来说
it may seem like a shock
这可能会让他们感到惊讶
that a big evolution was running two programs at once instead of just one.
从一次运行1个程序，到2个，竟是一个大进步
Yeah, the telegraph what?
对 电报什么？
This is too much of a setup.
这简直是预设好的
But you know the telegraph.
但你知道电报
Do you know Morse code?
你知道摩尔斯电码吗？
Man, there you go.
I mean, you know what it is.
我意思，你知道它是什么意思
I don't know actual Morse code.
我不懂摩尔斯电码
That's pretty cool.
这挺酷的
But anyways, so you want this.
不过 想要
The idea was, hey, let, you have different implementations
这个想法是，让，这有不同的实现
but let each user space process
让每个用户空间进程
have access to what it thinks is all of the memory that it needs.
让它以为，能访问到所需的全部内存
But the operating system manages this lie
但操作系统会管好这个‘错觉’
so that two different processes can each access
让两个不同的进程，都能访问
what they think is the exact same memory
它们认为的同一块内存
but they never touch and never see anything.
但它们 互不干扰
So the The job of the kernel is to support this.
所以内核的工作就是实现这个
So this is why
这就是为什么
what we're absolutely not focusing on in this class is
本课程中，完全不会涉及
any like how to write a Mac app,
比如如何编写 Mac 应用
how to write an iPhone app
如何编写 iPhone 应用
how to write any kind of app that runs on this operating system.
如何编写，运行在这个操作系统上的任何应用
Because fundamentally, we don't care about all of this.
因为我们根本不关心这些
The only thing we care about is how to talk to the operating system.
我们唯一关心的是如何与操作系统通信
Right.
对
And that's through just like most things it's through a system call.
和大多数操作系统一样，通过系统调用
So we call into the operating system.
所以我们通过调用进入操作系统
because that is the interface between user space and kernel
因为这就是用户空间和内核之间的接口
where the process can say
进程可以要求
do something for me, right?
给我做点事 对吧？
And then like Justin was saying
就像贾斯汀说的那样
so on the kernel side
在内核这边
the kernel needs to manage all these different things.
内核需要管理这些不同的事务
The kernel also has its own stuff that it's doing.
内核也有自己的事要做
So it thinks about it in the form of a task.
它也是以任务的形式来处理
So you have different tasks that are doing different things.
所以有不同的任务在处理不同的事情
They get, I don't know
它们会……我也不清楚
have you guys taken like operating systems?
你们学过操作系统这门课吗？
So you know about like preempting
所以你们知道抢占
and like sharing resources and stuff, right?
还有资源共享之类的 对吧？
To make sure you don't deadlock, all this cool stuff.
确保不会死锁 这些事
But like I said, this Frankenstein thing
但就像我说的 这个拼凑怪物
rather than just saying, well, this is beautiful.
它没有直观的美
Like Linux, you could just say like Linux is the kernel
像 Linux 你可以直接说 Linux 就是内核
and it sure it has different components
当然 它有不同的组件
but it says one box, like Linux syscalls. When you look at the thing, right?
但它们可被视为一类 比如 Linux 系统调用 对吧？
You can see all the syscalls.
你能看到所有的系统调用
Here they're
这里
the BSD system calls and the mach system calls are completely different.
BSD 系统调用和 mach 系统调用 完全不同
And the way to think about it is the
理解这一点的关键是
it's not like a
这并不是说
what is it called
怎么说来着
like first among equals
平等中的首位（群龙之首）
or like where they're actually like at the same level.
他们实际在同一层级
Like one has to subsume the other
但一个必须包含另一个
which is the mach kernel is kind of like the real core.
这让 mach 内核更像是真正的核心
So because in like BSD, just like Linux
在 BSD 中跟 Linux 一样
you have the concept of like a task
有一个类似任务的概念
I can't remember if they call it a thread or something
我不记得他们是不是叫它线程了
but that just calls into the mach part
但它会调用进入mach
to be like what's the current thread and like passes it back.
当前的线程是什么 并将其返回
So it doesn't keep
所以它不会保留
because if you think about it, this makes sense, right?
因为仔细想想 这是有道理的 对吧？
You don't want to keep two different notions of like
你不想在内核中保留两种不同的概念
what is a process in two different places in your operating system kernel?
当一个进程出现在内核的2个不同地方，会是个什么情况
Because if you ever get them desynced
因为如果它们不同步了
you'll have absolute like calamity.
你会遇到大麻烦
So the source of truth is the mach kernel.
所以 mach 内核
It mainly handles like IPC
它主要负责进程间通信
like we talked about and we're going to get into next week of communication there.
像我们说过的，且下周会进一步讨论
Also does all the virtual memory.
它还负责虚拟内存
So this is why it's a super important part.
这就是为什么它非常重要
Protected memory, scheduling, preempting
保护内存、调度和抢占
I guess console IO
还有控制台的输入输出
whereas the BSD side does a lot more stuff that you're familiar with,
而 BSD 这边则负责你熟悉的许多其他功能
like file systems, networking
如文件系统和网络
the whole TCP IP stack is in here.
整个 TCP/IP 栈都在这里
BSD sockets, libraries, POSIX stuff
BSD 套接字、库和 POSIX 内容
I don't know, anything in there.
我不知道里面还有什么内容
So questions on this?
所以对此有什么问题吗？
Yeah.
问吧
Say it louder.
大声点说
yeah
嗯
so you will find out next week
下周就知道了
i don't want to yeah give it away
我不想提前透露
i mean we'll get into it
我们会深入讨论的
but there actually are
但实际上
what's interesting is there are fundamental differences
有趣的是，有一些根本上的差异
in how in what types of ipc they allow
在它们允许的进程间通信类型
so there's things that you can do with um uh port
你可以用 mach 端口做一些事
i think it's mach ports is what they're called
我记得 它们被称为 mach 端口
uh essentially the core difference
核心差异
which i'll is uh they are unidirectional not bi-directional
它们是单向的 而不是双向的
so you can have a port that only allows you to send or only allows you to receive
所以你可以拿到一个端口，它只能发，或者收
and so you can do interesting things with that
你可以用这种方式做很多有趣的事情
that you can't necessarily do with sockets
这些你可以不用socket实现
i don't know if there's like a practical difference
我不知道这有没有实际意义的区别
but it's interesting um
但确实很有趣
and you can also it has the uh
它还有
It has the concepts of privileges to it and also the ability
它有特权级的概念，还有
because the operating system controls all the ports
因为操作系统控制所有端口
so you can share that port
所以你可以共享这个端口
and delegate it to another process
并委托给另一个进程
and now it has those same rights that you had.
现在它有和你相同的权限
You can also give somebody a port with a right
你还可以，将要分享端口的权限
that says don't allow them to pass it on to anyone else.
设置成不许传递给别人
So this is how I
这就是
this is actually like these ports and this concept is
实际上
how the operating system allows you to do debugging
操作系统就是按照这个概念，让你进行调试
and get super privileged access to things.
和获得超级权限，访问东西的
So it actually, I mean
所以说 我意思是
I don't know.
我也不知道
Why am I talking about this?
我为什么说到这个？
We'll talk about this next week.
我们下星期再讲
Anyways, okay.
好吧 不管怎样
Other questions about this?
还有其他问题吗？
Sorry.
对不起
What do you mean by stable?
你说的稳定是什么意思？
Hmm.
嗯
Great question.
好问题
Our goal today is
我们今天的目标是
we're going to walk through and figure out exactly what happens on a syscall.
弄清楚系统调用具体是怎么回事
But that won't answer your question of if it's stable or not
但这无法回答它是否稳定的问题
until you diff it over multiple versions.
除非你在多个版本之间进行对比
It's stable-ish.
还算挺稳定的
I think like as a, it is because
我觉得 这是因为
so I think the way to think about those things, right
我觉得 应该这样想
is on Windows you're not really supposed to directly
在windows上，你不应该直接
like a user space app is not supposed to call a system call.
用户空间的应用不该直接调用系统调用
There's the, what's the library? Win32 DLL or Win64 DLL.
有个什么库来着？Win32 DLL 还是 Win64 DLL
There's a user space DLL that on Windows you are supposed to call this DLL
在windows上，你应该调用一个在用户空间的dll
or NT32DLL.
还是 NTDLL.dll
What is it?
是什么呢？
Yeah. Kernel 32 DLL or whatever it is.
对 Kernel32.DLL 或别的，不管了
Anyways, there's a DLL
总之 有个 DLL
which is a user space library that you call.
一个你可以调用的用户空间库
It's basically like a libC for the kernel.
它就像是内核的 libC
Like you call into there
你调用进入它
and then it translates whatever you're doing
然后它将你的操作
into a system call that the kernel does
转换成内核执行的系统调用
and it sends it back and that translates it back.
等内核将结果发回，它再转换回来
So this way, as long as
所以这样 只要
Microsoft knows that all the user space apps
微软知道 这样对于用户空间应用
that they're not going to break compatibility go through there.
不会破坏兼容性
They can do all kinds of crazy, clever stuff in there
微软可以在kernel32.dll中做修改
to deal with different OS versions
以应对不同操作系统版本
and the OS can change.
就可以放心改操作系统了
Whereas on Linux, the boundary is on the system call layer.
而在 Linux 上 做了系统调用分层
So if you want to be able to run an app always from an old version of Linux to a new version
如果你想让一个程序能兼容新老linux版本
the system call numbers have to remain constant.
那么系统调用号需保持不变
So Apple is much more in that camp, I would say, where they...
所以我认为苹果在这方面更为慎重 他们......
The interface is between the user space app and the system call interface is the AVI.
用户应用和系统调用之间的接口是AVI
But the caveat and the ish is that unlike Windows
但是与 Windows 不同的是
which prides itself on being able to take an app from Windows 95.
Windows 以能够支持从 Windows 95 时代的应用而自豪
Have you guys heard the stories about Windows where like they add
你们听过 Windows 会添加
there are literal shims in either the operating system or this DLL that say
操作系统或 DLL 中有修补代码
if your application is SimCity, then... and it's targeting Windows 95
如果你的应用是《模拟城市》 并且系统是 Windows 95
then do this behavior that it's expecting
那么就执行这个操作
but that's wrong and incorrect behavior
但这种行为是错的，是不对的
because they tried to take the operating system
因为他们试图修改操作系统
they upgraded the operating system
他们升级了操作系统
realized that the app fails
发现应用程序无法运行
they would add in app-specific shims in the OS
他们会在系统中，添加特定应用的兼容代码
to support those applications.
来支持这些应用
So Windows has prided themselves on this backwards compatibility.
所以 Windows 一直以向后兼容性为荣
Apple does not have that at all.
Apple 完全不会这样做
So there's absolutely no guarantee
所以完全不能保证
that your app that worked on this thing will work on the next thing.
能在这个系统运行的应用，也能在后面的运行
They'll just be like, yeah you're just going to have to recompile it.
他们会说，你只需要重新编译就行
Like, tough.
没办法 就是这么严苛
So that, I think
所以 我觉得
they don't force themselves into having that compatibility.
他们不会硬生生地实现那种兼容性
But it's pretty stable, I think.
但我觉得它很稳定
And maybe we can look at, like the Git history and see how often it changes.
我们可以看看 Git 历史记录 看看它多久改一次
I think not very often.
我觉得不会经常改
Cool. All right.
酷，好的
In fact, it's 5.30.
现在 5 点 30 了
Let's take a five-minute break.
我们休息五分钟
And then we'll get back to it.
然后继续
And then we'll...
接下来我们...
Read the source.
看一下代码
All right, Twitch, we're taking a break.
好了 Twitch 咱们休息一下
Go turn on the TV
去把电视打开
and watch an ad or something.
看看广告之类的
Okay, we're about to come back.
好的 我们马上回来
We're just testing that these changes worked.
我们正在测试这些改动是否有效
I'm feeling pretty confident about it.
我对此很有信心
The audience is not.
观众却不这样认为
They're booing and they were hissing when the audio was off.
禁音时，他们都在嘘
so hopefully we can prove them incorrect with this.
希望能证明他们是错的
I don't want to wait like five minutes.  Okay.
我不想等五分钟 好吧
This is the other thing.
这是另一点
So taking, this does take a long time.
这需要很长时间
So yanking the files to your local machine and getting it to run locally will be
把文件拉到本地机器上运行
you'll be much better.
会好很多
And you should be able to
你应该能
this previous emulator is also open source.
这个previous模拟器也是开源的
So you should be able to compile it on your own system and get it to run.
所以你可以在自己的系统上编译并运行它
Since you all run Linux
因为你们都用 Linux
this should be very easy
这应该很简单
because it just needs an X server to run.
因为它只需要一个 X 服务器就能运行
Okay.
好的
This actually gets to a good point of,
这引出一个好的点
any kind of thing when doing development or vulnerability analysis or exploitation
无论是在程序开发、漏洞分析还是漏洞利用开发时
the shorter you can make your test, make a change, test it, loop
测试、修改、再测试的循环越短
the happier you will be as a person.
你的心情就会越好
Sitting here waiting for this stupid thing to just do this
坐等这破事
can drive you crazy
会让人抓狂
so have other ways of doing it
用别的方法做这个
I would recommend...
我推荐
Okay, so as this is going
好的 让它在这跑着
we can go back and start talking about the source.
我们回过头来谈谈源代码
So since they have source
既然有源代码
we should use it.
我们就可以用它
We should not be silly and not use it.
我们可不能傻到不用它
That would be not cool.
那就不酷了
So, oh, no, why would you go there?
所以 哦，怎么跑这来了？
Well, because you're...
嗯 因为你……
So once I find it.
所以 等我找到它
Okay, so you can actually go.
好的 你可以开始了
Apple has a whole open source Apple thing.
苹果有一整套开源项目
You can see all the open source stuff.
你可以看到所有开源的内容
There are stuff that we are absolutely not gonna talk about.
有些我们肯定不会讨论
Why aren't we gonna talk about Swift?
为什么我们不讨论 Swift？
That may not be true. I don't know.
那可能不对 我不清楚
I've heard good things.
我听到了些好的回答
Yeah, Swift is for making user mode programs.
是的 Swift 用于编写用户模式程序
And Swift, if you make a user mode program in Swift
如果你用 Swift 编写用户模式程序
it has to talk to the kernel and eventually it will need to make a syscall
它需要与内核通信，最终它会进行系统调用
and so you can all do that in C. You don't need Swift to do any of that.
你用 C 语言也可以做这些 不需要用 Swift
I don't know.
我不知道
I guess if somebody's really crazy
如果有人足够疯狂
they can write their exploits in Swift
他们可以用 Swift 写漏洞利用程序
but I would absolutely not recommend it.
但我绝对不建议这样做
You should be doing your stuff in C when you're talking to the kernel.
当程序要与内核交互时，你应该用 C 编写
They also do Kubernetes.
他们还有 Kubernetes 相关的
They also create WebKit.
他们还开发了 WebKit 浏览器引擎
So WebKit is an open source.
WebKit 是一个开源的
I believe it's like the content engine of like parsing HTML and doing all this stuff.
我记得，它主要用于解析和处理HTML相关功能
So you can actually
所以你可以
which is used in a ton of places.
它广泛应用于各种场景
Like WebKit is actually used in a lot of browsing engines.
WebKit 实际上被用在很多浏览器引擎里
And so you can kind of see this cool, like almost cycle of life, right?
这几乎是一个生态圈，对吧
Where like next XNU was on next and.
XNU 内核在NextStep机器上
That created the web
用它创建了web
and then eventually the people that made that created WebKit
然后那些人又创建了 WebKit
this open browser engine
这个开源的浏览器引擎
and then gave it back.
然后再把它贡献回去
So I think that's kind of cool.
我觉得这挺酷的
There's a lot of projects that they have that are open source.
他们有很多项目都是开源的
I don't know what this is.
我不知道这是什么
FoundationDB, MLX, CareKit, ResearchKit.
maybe some of you all need this.
也许你们有些人用得上这个
Oh, Medical Research.
哦 医学研究
Okay.
好的
Password Manager Researches.
密码资源管理器
Interesting.
真有趣
Oh, interesting, that they participate in.
哦有趣 他们参与了
So they're big in LLVM and Clang.
他们在 LLVM 和 Clang 很活跃
Clang is the default compiler that they use.
Clang 是他们默认的编译器
Anyways, so let's see what are all the C?
好的，看看有哪些 C 开发的？
Okay, so that's everything that's on there.
这就是上面所有的内容
If you wanted to poke around it
如果你想深入了解一下
they used to just distribute like tarballs.
他们以前都是直接分发 tarball 文件
So there would just be a massive list
所以会有个长长的列表
with all of these tarballs of their source releases.
包含所有发布的源码 tarball
Ironically, they now have everything on, GitHub
讽刺的是 他们现在把所有东西都放在了 GitHub 上
and the reason I say ironically is because GitHub is owned by Microsoft
我说讽刺，是因为 GitHub 是微软的
so the fact that the company that they were fighting for so long
他们曾经长期对抗的公司
now they rely on them
现在却依赖这家公司
for distributing their own code is very bizarre to me.
来分发自己的代码 这感觉很奇怪
And so you can see
你可以看到
you can get very lost in here.
这里很容易让人迷失方向
I mean, you can poke around all you want
你可以随便逛逛
but there's like 509 repositories in here.
这里有 509 个仓库
The pinned repositories are probably where you all want to start.
这些置顶的项目，你们大概率想从这里开始
I was actually talking to somebody, some people here.
我跟这里的一些人聊过
I don't know when this was last updated, but
我不知道最后一次更新是什么时候
yeah, three years ago.
三年前
Actually, so Apple did sell like an OS X server.
其实 苹果确实出售过 OS X 服务器
So like a server version of their whole operating system.
他们服务器的操作系统
I don't think anyone uses this.
我觉得没人用了
This is like a super out-of-date thing
这东西已经过时了
and I don't even think they support it or sell it now or anything.
他们现在好像也不支持，不卖了
But you can find Mac OS, the iOS
但你还能找到 Mac OS 和 iOS
and I don't know what this developer's tools thing is.
还有这个，我不太清楚的 开发者工具
And clicking on here
点击进入这里
they're basically using Git submodules
他们基本上是使用 Git 子模块
in order to point to other commits in the other repositories.
来指向其他仓库中的提交
And the other tricky thing here is
另一个问题是
you'd see like, oh, main.
一看到  main
Yes, Mac OS 14.0.
Mac OS 14.0
Great. This is where we absolutely are.
好的 我们现在肯定在这里
I don't know that that's the latest.
不确定这是否是最新版
You have to either go to branches or tags.
你可以去分支或标签
Tags, yeah.
标签 没错
So tags is a better thing.
所以看标签更好
You can see they actually just pushed a release three weeks ago for Mac OS 14.6
你可以看到 他们三周前发布了 Mac OS 14.6
which actually is a pretty good...
这个版本其实挺不错的……
Let's see.
我们来看看
This was in July, so July, August, September.
这是在七月发布的 七月、八月、九月（视频录制月份）
Yeah, two-month gap before releasing it.
发布前确实隔了两个月
It's pretty good.
还不错
But the other thing you'll notice is
还有
so you want to use the tags.
所以要看Tags标签
The tags are absolutely how they do all this thing.
标签是他们处理这一切的关键
And then, wait, no I don't want the commit.
我不想看commit记录
I want to browse the tag.
我想看看标签
So they have a bunch of directories in here.
这里有好几个目录
Each of these is
这里的每一个都是
its own project that's basically now pinned to that version
它们自己项目的一个固定版本
that works with that distribution of the entire operating system.
放在这个操作系统版本发布
So for this purposes
为此
we'll call like operating system kind of everything, all this junk.
这一大堆东西我们也称为操作系统
And then we'll talk about XNU is like the kernel that we'll actually focus on.
之后我们会讨论XNU，它是我们实际关注的内核
So I have absolutely no idea what all this stuff is.
所以我完全不知道这些东西是什么
Some of the stuff I kind of have a rough idea
有些东西我大概有点概念
but other stuff I don't.
但其他的我就不知道了
Some of it is user space things like...
有些是用户空间的东西 比如...
Like, oh, there's, was there libc?
比如 这里有 libc 吗？
Yeah, there libc is open source
有，libc 是开源的
that you can just go check out that runs in user space
你可以看看，它运行在用户空间
and that the user space programs use.
并被用户空间程序使用
I bet you could find in there one of the big things they did within the last year was
我肯定你能找到，去年他们做的最大的修改之一，
the user space allocator always zeros pages, like user,
用户空间的内存分配器 总会清零 内存页面
sorry, not pages, but zeros memory on a free.
抱歉 不是内存页面 而是在释放内存时清零
So to reduce the chances of a use after free or other weird stuff,
这样可以减少释放后再使用或出现其他奇怪问题的几率
it just like every time you free memory, it gets zeroed.
每次释放内存时，它都会被清零
And so...
所以......
I thought that's pretty interesting.
我觉得这挺有意思的
I bet that logic is in there.
我相信它里面有这个机制
WebKit, like we said, so the version of WebKit.
WebKit 我们之前说的，这是他的版本
Apache, this is kind of weird that they do this
Apache，放它进来做挺奇怪的
but things like Bash
但像 Bash 这样的
even like I know some of you know, well
像，我知道你们有人知道
I guess fake Adam that was here the first day loves Bash
第一天的那个假Adam（Yan），特别喜欢 Bash
and so maybe you can troll him
也许你们可以戏弄一下他
by finding subtle differences that Apple has made in this version of Bash
找一个苹果改过的，与原版有微妙差异的bash
which is the version that they ship
就是这里他们发的版本
that maybe makes some of the Linux Luminarium problems even crazier or not as useful
放到linux上 可能会让一些 Linux 问题更严重  或不好用
so there's a lot of like user space apps
这里有许多用户空间的应用程序
and a bunch of junk in here curl file anyways
还有很多其他的工具 比如 curl、file
so you can explore this your heart's content
所以你可以尽情探索这些库
libraries a ton of libraries libxml2
有很多库 比如 libxml2
this is one if you wanted to look for bugs
如果想找漏洞 这是个好地方
this would be a great place to look for it in an xml parser
XML 解析器是个好目标
people have found cool bugs in there
人们在那里，发现了一些很酷的漏洞
let's see python
再看看， Python
even the python version that they ship is
他们提供的 Python 版本
I actually don't know if it's customized or they've forked it completely.
我不知道是定制化过的，还是完全拷过去的
I've never done like a diff to see what's what.
我没用diff看过两者差异
Ruby, rsync.
And then I'm just naming things.
我就说说名字
Vim, if you like Vim.
Vim 如果你喜欢Vim的话
And then all the way at the bottom, you have XNU.
然后最底部是 XNU
So this is where the heart of everything is.
这里就是一切的核心
You go in here.
你进到这里
Now this is the
现在这是
and this should be tagged.
标签应该是
Yeah, so what's this? 14...
嗯 这个版本是  14...
10... Wow.
10... 哇
So the other super annoying thing is
另一件特别让人头疼的是
that there's different version numbers.
版本号各不相同
So there's some chart.
这里有个表格
I think it's in here.
应该就在这
Yeah.
嗯
So there's like, oh, no, that's, oh, see, HomePod software.
哦 看 HomePod 软件
So they...
所以他们……
Anyway, so there's versions that you may be used to thinking about,
有你可能比较熟悉的版本
like your Mac OS version.
比如 MacOS 版本
Like, let's see this Mac is probably running Sonoma, which is 14.6.1.
比如说，这台 Mac 运行的是 Sonoma 即 14.6.1
Important thing here is that
这里重要的是
this other thing is like a unique hash or part of a unique identifier
这个东西像个唯一的哈希 或是唯一标识符的一部分
that identifies usually this specific...
通常用于识别...
I think it goes back to the kernel.
我认为这个标识内核
And your iPhone, so you have iOS. I don't know what version is it on?
还有 iPhone， iOS  多少多少
16, 17, 18, something, a version number.
16、17、18 某一个版本号
But then you have that.
然后是
You have Darwin numbers.
Darwin 版本号
Darwin has different numbers
Darwin 有不同的版本号
which is like the whole thing.
这就像整个系统
And then you have the actual XNU numbers
然后是实际的 XNU 版本号
which is what we looked at in here.
就是我们这里看到的
Like these are all different XNU numbers.
这些都是不同的 XNU 版本号
I don't know exactly what they mean or how to parse them.
我不知道它们具体代表什么，或该怎么解析
You can think of them just as opaque.
你可以认为它们是不透明的
But you should always be able to do...
但你应该能...
I'm not here.
我不在
Wait, did it not work?
等等 静音时的修改失败了吗？
Sorry, we have to check if it works.
抱歉 我们得检查一下
This is critical.
这太关键了
Where's my thing?
我的东西呢？
That seems bad.
这不太妙
I know.  Okay.
我知道 好的
I don't care that much.
我没那么在乎
I mean, except for the fact that this is insane.
我是说 这太怪了
I am control d.
我按了ctrl d
That's how I exit.
这就是我退出的方法
All right.
好吧
what?
什么
It's supposed to do...
他本应...
Where's the stupid thing?
那玩意儿在哪儿？
Searching for open was a bad idea.
查找 open 真是个糟糕的主意
W orld W ide W eb.app.
Yeah.
嗯
The keystroke missed there.
那儿的按键没打到
That's so annoying.
真烦人
Well, all right.
好吧 行
I'll figure out what I can do to make this run better.
我会想出办法让这运行得更好
Can you write it to a script and execute the script?
你能把它写成脚本然后执行吗？
You still need to type in stuff to execute it is the problem.
你还需要输入字符来执行 这就是问题所在
The other thing is this is all super brittle
另外 这一切都非常脆弱
because it was written a long time ago
因为这代码是很久以前写的
and the more I mess with it
而且我改的越多
the more I'm likely to just absolutely mess things up.
就越容易彻底搞砸
Okay, let's go back.
好了 我们回去
Version numbers, great.
版本号 很好
You can see, yeah, anyways.
你能看到 总之
All the stuff in here.
这里所有的东西
Oh, that's why I was getting to a terminal.
哦 这就是我为什么要进终端
So I could show you terminal.
我可以给你演示下终端
And I could show you.
也可以给你看看
Yeah, so in the uname
嗯 在 uname 中
you can see the Darwin version, 23.6.
你可以看到 Darwin 23.6
And then you can see the XNU version.
还能看到 XNU 版本
And then it's the release kernel on ARM64.
接着是 说该内核运行在ARM64上
This last one is like the machine, like specific to, there's
最后的这个 是特定于某台机器的 比如
because if you think about it
因为你想一下
so there's like release, there's ARM64 that could apply to a Mac
ARM64 芯片有的用在 Mac
or it could apply to an iPhone or something.
或用在iPhone之类的
So there's different targets in here
这里有不同的目标（T...）
of what actual specific machine to target.
指具体的机器类别
And I'm not sure what this part is.
我不确定这一部分是什么
So anyways, this is how you can figure out where you are.
总之 这是确定版本的方法
And then if we wanted to find this exact kernel version
然后 如果我们想找到这个具体的内核版本
we'd look at like
我们看
this is actually probably it.
这应该就是了
No. because this is .2
不是这个 因为是 .2 版本
so it hasn't been open sourced yet.
它还没开源
This is probably something that's slightly,
这可能有些不同
I think if, let's see if we looked at about this Mac
我们来看看这台 Mac
what did we say? It was 14.6.1
之前说是多少？14.6.1
and this I would guess is 14.6.
我猜这个是 14.6
Yeah, which makes sense.
没错 这说得通
That's how we got here, right?
我们就是这样来的 对吧？
Through the distribution link.
通过这个链接
Mac OS, 14.6.
Mac OS 14.6
This is 14.
这个是 14
I'm running 14.6.1.
我用的是 14.6.1
which is not open source yet.
它还没有开源
If you really spend a lot of time doing this
如果你花了很多时间在这上
you will be live and die by these releases
你的命运就系在这些版本发布上了
because you want to see if they're killing one of your bugs or not killing your bugs.
因为你想知道你找到的bug有没有被修复
But sometimes they release them
但有时候他们会发布
sometimes they don't.
有时不发
Sometimes the person doing it forgets
有时候负责的人会忘了
and just doesn't do it.
然后就不发了
I don't know what their internal criteria is.
我不知道他们内部的标准是什么
So good luck.
所以祝你好运
Okay.
好的
Cool.
And theoretically, I guess you can
理论上 你可以
pull down all of that entire distribution.
下载整个发布包
I think I've tried that once
我试过一次
but it takes up like a ton of room of like all those different directories.
但它会占用大量空间 一堆不同的项目目录
So we have that directory.
我们有那个目录
And so now we will start exploring that directory.
现在我们来探索这个目录
We were in here, 14.1.
我们在 14.1
Let's browse there.
我们去看看
So you would think, well, this is great.
你可能会觉得 这太棒了
Just like any good software system
就像任何好的软件系统一样
there's a how to build.
有一个构建指南
Have any of you taken software from GitHub
你们有没有从 GitHub 下载过软件？
and you followed the README and tried to build it?
然后按照 README 尝试构建？
What would you say your success rate is?
你们的成功率大概是多少？
What was it, 15?
15% 吗？
I think that's pretty good, yeah.
我觉得这已经很不错了
Like maybe 50-ish percent.
大概 50%
All depends on how important the thing is that you're targeting.
这全看你的目标有多重要
And so similar things apply here.
所以这里也一样
So maybe they're late for their test next one.
下次考试说不定他们也会迟到
What are you doing?
你在做什么？
Stop.
停
So that's why people write
所以人们会写
especially when there was the change from Intel to Apple Silicon.
尤其是在从 Intel 切换到 Apple Silicon 的时候
I'll talk about this a little bit
我会简要讲一下
but there are people that write entire blog posts
有些人会专门写博客
of how to actually compile the kernel
讲解如何编译内核
because it doesn't always cleanly just build.
因为编译并不总是那么顺利
And you have to install
而且你还需要安装
so Xcode is the development environment.
Xcode 是开发环境
Ooh, 5% online that they said their thing does.
哦 线上有人说成功率 5%
So you have to install the right version.
所以你得安装正确的版本
You have to download a kernel development kit
你需要下载内核开发套件
if you're building on Apple Silicon Macs.
如果你是在 Apple Silicon 的 Mac 上开发
Or sorry, if you're building an ARM target.
抱歉 如果你编译的目标是 ARM架构
The kernel development kit.
内核开发套件
What was it?
什么？
Oh, you guys want to see stuff?
哦 你们想看看吗？
Wow. You don't just trust me when I say things?
哇。你们不相信我说的吗？
Okay.
好的
So anyways, this is a giant blog post.
所以 总之这是一篇很长的博客
It's all about how to actually build this version of 11.2.
主要是讲如何实际构建 11.2 版本
And then when version 12 came out
然后 12 版本出来后
this did not work anymore.
这篇就不行了
And I know because I've tried to build 12
我知道 因为我试过构建 12 版本
and I have a way of doing it
而且我有个成功的方法
but I'll share with you in a second.
等会儿我就和你们分享
Yeah, you should be able to...
是的 你应该能做到……
I still don't 100% know.
我还不是完全确定
And if somebody can verify this for me, there is an
如果有人能帮我核实一下
so there's an Apple developer website
所以有一个苹果开发者网站
which is what we're looking at here.
就是我们现在看到的
Where's my phone?
我的手机呢？
Oh, security.
哦 安全啊
It's too secure.
太安全了
Where's my two-factor?
我的双因子验证呢
Oh, because I don't have one.
哦 因为我没有
Yeah, that's right.
是的
Sorry, this is a different account than the one I use.
抱歉 这不是我常用的账号
I actually don't have any Apple devices
我手头没有苹果设备
in case you can't see.
你可能没看到
Okay, cool.
好的 没问题
I guess nobody can actually do anything with this.
我猜没人能利用这个验证码
This is the beauty of one-time passwords.
这就是一次性密码的妙处
Trust, but it doesn't matter.
坚持访问 没事
It's private browsing.
这是隐私模式浏览
Okay, so I think...
好 我感觉...
Theoretically, you should be able to
理论上 你可以
create an Apple developer account without paying
免费创建苹果开发者账户
because you can pay to like launch apps on the app store.
因为你可以付费 上架应用 到谷歌应用商店
You have to pay like $100 with a developer account.
你需要用开发者账户支付，好像，100 美元
I think you can just create a development account and then.
我觉得你可以直接创建一个开发账户
Yeah, so this is where all the kernel debug kits are.
所有内核调试工具包都在这
This is a big
这可是个大文件
I think it's like a 12 gig download
大概有 12GB
that has the release kernel, a development kernel, and a KASAN kernel.
包含了发布内核、开发内核和 KASAN 内核
So KASAN is like user space ASAN
KASAN 就像用户空间的 ASAN 一样
but in the kernel it can detect use after frees,
但在内核中，它可以检查UAF
writing out of bounds writes, these kinds of things.
越界写入等类似问题
And so what you need to do is find the exact
你需要找到确切的
so this is that hash that I was talking about here.
这就是我之前提到的哈希值
That's like what you need to find to get your version.
这就是你需要找的 以便获取你的版本
We're definitely not going to find ours here
这里肯定找不到我们要找的
but we can at least look.
但我们至少可以看一看
Oh, it is. Okay.
哦 还真有 好的
Yeah, so I have the 14.6.1 build.
是的 我用的是 14.6.1 版本
It also has symbols in here
这里面有内核符号
and there's LLDB macros that help with debugging the kernel.
还有 LLDB 宏 能帮助调试内核
It's actually really cool.
这真的很赞
The output, I think, in some cases, can be even better than GDB
某些情况下 输出甚至比 GDB 还好
but to build the stuff
但要编译构建这个
you have to have that on your machine and installed to actually do it.
你需要在你的电脑上装好这个
On the target machines
在目标环境上
when you need it
当你需要时
I think this will already be installed
那时应该已经装好了
so it shouldn't be an issue
所以应该没问题
and you won't have to think about it, hopefully.
希望你不需要再操心这个
But we'll see.
不过到时候再说
Okay, yeah.
好的 嗯
So KDK package, you need to install it, yada, yada, yada.
所以 KDK 包 你得装上 等等
The version number needs to be right.
版本号一定要对
It's also insane
还有一点很疯狂
there are sometimes different builds for the exact same version number.
有时候不同的构建，会有同一个版本号
And sometimes you'll get into situations
有时候还会遇到这样的情况
where You will have the source version of a 12-point whatever
你有某个 12.几 版本的源码
but not the KDK version
但没有对应的 KDK 版本
so you can't even build it
所以你根本编译构建不了
because it doesn't have the right things.
因为它缺少对应的东西
I think there's something in here that they link to for ARM
我觉得 这里链接的 有些运行在ARM上的东西
that's part of the boot process that is not open source
是启动过程的一部分 不是开源的
and that's what it needs for the ARM part
这是使用 ARM 组件的要求
but I haven't dug into it a ton.
但我没深入研究过
So, yeah, this is, I guess
这个是
I can't make this an assignment
我不能把它留作作业
because this doesn't make sense
这不合理
because not all of you have Apple devices.
不是每个人都有苹果设备
But one of the things I did as part of preparing for this class
但我为这门课做的一个准备是
is try to get build scripts working for different versions.
尝试用脚本成功构建不同版本
So I have one for 11.2.
所以我有一个编译 11.2 版本的
So these are make files.
这些都是 make 文件
You just run make
你只需要运行 make 就行了
and it builds the whole thing for you.
它会帮你构建整个项目
Let's test it out.
我们来测试一下
Which one do we want to build, 11.2 or 12.5?
我们构建哪个版本 11.2 还是 12.5？
12.5, just because the number's higher?
12.5 就因为版本号更高吗？
And you can see these patches.
你可以看到这些补丁
So I had to patch.
我必须打补丁
This one wasn't the OS so much as like the build environment needed to be patched.
这个问题不是出在操作系统，而是构建环境需要打补丁
Oh, wait, wait. I didn't read the readme.
等一下 我还没看README
This requires the KDK
这需要 KDK
which I already have installed.
我已经安装了
So I will do it like this.
所以我这样做
We pass this environment variable.
传入这个环境变量
So I've obviously already set up all that stuff
这些我已经设置好了
but it has to like
但它必须
There's pre stuff that it needs to compile to build tools
有一些前置的工具需要编译
that then it uses while building the kernel and it uses those tools.
构建内核时，会用到这些工具
And like it, the kernel, the code
代码是这样
I don't know if the kernel,
内核 我不确定
but the code in the repo, like hard codes them to specific directories.
但仓库中的代码，硬编码了特定的目录
So I patched them so that they look at this local bin folder that gets created.
所以我对它们进行了修补，让它们去到刚创建的bin目录
And so anyways,
总之
my ask is what would be great is if
我希望
this is an open source thing
这是开源的
like it's public
是公开的
And we're just building open source stuff.
我们构建了一个开源项目
So if you all who have access to a Mac
所以 如果有 Mac 的朋友
if you want to expand this by adding new versions
如果你想扩展这个项目 增加新内核版本构建支持
I think the community would really benefit because
我认为社区会因此受益
basically this last blog post was one of the latest ones that I saw of
这是我最近看到的一篇博客文章
like, here's how to compile this thing.
内容主要讲如何编译这个东西
And I'm like, great.
我觉得 太好了
We have a script for 11.
我们有针对 11 的脚本了
It should be easy of 12.
改一个 12 的版本应该很容易
And 12.5...
还有 12.5...
Let's see, what was that?
等等 那是什么？
This was 12.5 was, yeah, July 20th, 2022.
12.5 版本是在 2022 年 7 月 20 日发布的
So this is the one I'm targeting for the physical devices
我准备用这个版本
because I know I can build it
因为我能构建它
and I know I have the KDK for it
而且我有它的 KDK
and I think I can
还能
that that will work and we can just study that.
这样就行了 然后我们可以直接研究
So anyways, I think it'd be cool.
总之 我觉得它很不错
Oh no, what?
哦 不！ 什么？
Oh, I must have some other diffs that I didn't actually do.
哦 我肯定还有一些没做的改动
How do I diff two directories?
怎么比较两个目录？
Anybody know?
有谁知道吗？
Like this?
这样对吗？
git diff -r?
I don't think that's right.
我觉得不太对
It's like this.
应该是这样
Naur, right?
Naur 对吧？
Yeah.
对
Ah, see?
啊 看到没？
I have uncommitted changes that I need to patch.
我的补丁有未提交的更改
Oh yeah, this was an insane bug, where somehow
哦 对了 这是个诡异的 bug 也不知道为什么
I think it's because we're using a newer compiler
可能是因为我们用了新版的编译器
and null is macroed to something else that's not, I think to zero
null 被宏定义成了其他东西 好像变成0了
but this function returns booleans
但这个函数要返回布尔类型值
and so it has to return false or true
所以它必须返回 false 或 true
and the I don't know if this ever compiled.
我不知道这是否编译通过过
This doesn't make sense that this compiled, but anyways, yes
很难相信 它编译通过过 不过 好吧
I do recall doing this, but okay.
我记得我这么做过 不过就这样吧
So this is a good thing.
这是件好事
I need to fix this because this doesn't work.
我需要修复这个问题 因为它不起作用
So thanks for making a demo on the one that doesn't work.
多谢 做了这个不能用的示例
Random student in the audience.
的观众中的某位同学
Yeah, cool.
好的 真酷！
Okay, so anyways,
好的 总之
I think that'd be a cool outcome of this course
这门课一定会很有意义
if we can help the community.
如果我们能帮到社区
I will say if anybody tries the latest, latest versions, like 14
如果有人尝试最新版本 比如 14
I absolutely cannot get them to compile because...
我根本编译不了 因为……
As we'll learn next week
下周我们会学到
there's the raw message passing IPC
在原始的消息传递 IPC 上
but then Apple has built another layer on top of that
苹果在其上又加了一层
where they define messages to call to other,
在这层中 他们定义了用于调用其他进程的消息
basically like an inter-procedure language that you can define interfaces
基本上就像一种可以定义接口的跨进程语言
and that way you can automatically compile code from there
这样就可以从那里自动编译代码
for the server and the client to do that communication and parsing and everything.
完成服务端与调用端通信，和解析等任务
They created some new format
他们开发了一种新的格式
and that's not in the version of Clang that I'm using.
它不在我用的 Clang 版本里
I don't know where this is.
我不知道这在哪
It's like using some option of Clang to compile these.
像是用了 Clang 的某些选项来编译这些
I think they're like MIG2 or MIGMach2.
我觉得它们可能是 MIG2 或 MIGMach2（不知道）
Anyways, I got into this thing
总之 我遇到了这个问题
but if we can solve that problem that'd be great.
如果我们能解决这个问题  那很好
There are a lot of people that would be very thankful
很多人会非常感谢
that we can solve this thing.
咱们解决这个问题
I think it'd be a fun project to extend this out
我觉得把这个项目扩展一下会很有趣
and it'd help you get familiar with it.
这也有助于你熟悉这东西
cause honestly
因为
when you're doing this real world stuff,
当你处理这些实际问题时
especially on, like we said, 15, 5% of things actually compile
尤其是像我们说的 只有 15%或5% 的概率能编译通过
but you still got to find bugs in them.
但你还得找里面的bug
So like get it to compile.
所以先让它能编译
Like that's like the first step of this stuff
漏洞挖掘第一步就是
is actually getting it to compile.
让代码能编译
And so, you know you can't just be like, well it doesn't work.
所以你不能上来就 “不行 跑不起来”
Like, I don't know, patch it, fix it, find the dependencies.
想办法解决它，比如，打补丁，修改它，找依赖
Like there was,
比如说 有个问题
oh yeah, the other the latest ones are missing header files
对了 有个问题是 新版本缺少头文件
that exist in earlier versions but don't exist in that version.
老版本有但在新版本中没了
And like, Is that good, bad?
这样是好是坏？
Can I just copy the old ones over?
我能直接复制旧的过来吗？
I don't know, that seems wrong, but weird.
不知道 这样做好像不对 但也挺 怪的
But you can learn a lot of things about software by making it build and work.
通过尝试编译软件，你能学到不少
Cool, okay.
好的 了解
So in the source
在源码中
we're already looking at it.
我们已经在看了
We can just go to the right back here.
我们直接回到这里
Cool, so now we're at the repo.
好的 现在我们到了仓库
And the other thing I think people
还有一件事 我觉得很多人
a lot of people
很多人都会
especially we think about doing, oh
特别是当我们考虑要
the latest come in the Clang repost from three years ago.
这里最新的clang是三年前的
Yeah, that seems wrong.
看着不对劲
Although maybe there's a tag that is latest
也可能是tag标的“最新”
that I don't have yet
但我还没看到
but I was using the Clang that ships with Xcode, the latest one.
但我用的是随 Xcode 一起发布的最新 Clang
A lot of mistakes that people make is either just diving into the code
很多人犯的错误是直接跳进代码
and not reading the documentation that is right there in front of you
而不去读眼前的文档
because you don't want to do that
因为你不愿意做这个
but you can learn a ton.
但你能学到很多
There's already so much stuff in here
这里已经有很多东西了
Although, I will warn you, does documentation compile?
不过我要提醒你 文档会参与编译吗？
What docs compile?
哪些文档会参与编译？
There's one software, I think.
应该是有一个软件
Huh?
啊？
Yeah, tech, I think.
对 应该是tech（不清楚，欢迎补充）
But it's more like a readable thing
但更像是个可读的东西
and I don't know that the docs actually compile
我不知道文档真会被编译吗
but they're part of the source code.
但它们是源代码的一部分
No newer branches.
没有新的分支
Thank you, JWU01.
谢谢 JWU01
So yeah, the docs can be out of date, right?
所以 文档可能会过时
The fundamental thing of they don't compile means
他们不参与编译
that like nobody's checking that it's actually maps to reality.
导致大概率没有人去检查它
So some of this stuff kind of maybe works.
所以这些内容可能有些管用
I don't know. It's like a good starting point.
不清楚，但它是一个很好的起点
You have to read this like an archeologist.
你要像考古学家一样，读这些
Like at one point people thought this
之前人们是这么想的
like that may not be what reality is in this software
但这可能不符合该软件现在的情况
but at least I know
但至少我知道
that at a certain point people thought this
之前有人这样想
and I can start from there.
我可以从这里开始
Yeah, so we are, okay.
好的 我们
Like I think all this stuff about like building kernel caches and booting it
我觉得 这些都是讲构建内核cache并启动它的
I think this is old stuff for older versions
这些应该是老版本的东西
but I would love to be proved wrong.
但我很愿意被证明是错的
Anyways, there's like a ton of stuff in here.
总之 这里有很多东西
What we are looking for is I think right at the top that I missed.
我们要找的 应该在最上面 但我漏掉了
Yeah.
嗯
So where is everything?
东西都在哪儿？
So we got this giant directory, external headers, setup, BSD, config, doc,
我们有一个大目录 包括外部头文件、设置、BSD、配置和文档
IO kit, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah, blah.
IO 套件，等等
Where is anything, right?
东西都在哪儿？
That's like one of the key things you need to understand
这是需要理解的一个关键点
as you start poking around things.
在探索这些文件的时候
This is kind of thinking of it as like
你可以这样理解 就像是
it'd be like going for a hike without having a map, right?
否则 就像没带地图去远足一样 对吧？
You're just like kind of poking around
你就像在随便摸索一样
and you can get pretty far
倒也能探索很远
just repping for things that you're interested in and reading code
只看你感兴趣的，读读代码
but ultimately it's better to kind of know
但最终 最好大致知道
roughly if I'm looking for this thing
如果你要找一个东西
where do I think it's going to be in this source code repository?
能大概知道它在代码仓库的什么位置
So such as you can look at this stuff.
比如 你看这个
So config, Configurations
所以 配置
this is where I think you can configure the version number.
估计你可以在这里配置版本号
Some tools that are used to set up.
一些用于设置的工具
External headers are very important.
外部头文件非常重要
These are used while building.
这些在编译构建时会用到
There's, we probably won't get into it
我们可能不会深入讨论IOKit
but Iokit is a C++ library to define drivers and kext
它是一个C++ 库 用于定义驱动程序和Kext
I always say kernel extensions
我通常会说内核扩展
but kx I don't know if that's how somebody says that
我不知道有没有人叫他kx
but I guess you could do it either way.
我估计怎么说都行
Kernel extensions.
内核扩展
Um, so as we, I mean
嗯 我是说
we will get to the point
我们会讲到这个
hopefully that you are popping kernel, uh, extensions.
希望你们正在攻击内核扩展
So under this may be of understanding how to
所以 为了理解如何
but this should all be documented.
这些应该有文档记录
So you probably don't need to look at this code necessarily.
所以你们可能不需要特意读这段代码
libsa bootstrap code for startup.
libsa 用于启动的引导代码
That would be kind of interesting to look at if you're looking for like pre-boot vulnerabilities
如果你们要找启动前的漏洞，会对这里感兴趣
uh, jailbreaking kind of things.
越狱之类的
libsyscall, this is super interesting.
libsyscall 这个非常有趣
I don't think I've ever looked in here.
我没看过这里面的内容
This is maybe where you'd think
你可能会以为
where you'd go of like this is where system calls go.
这里是系统调用的实现
But I think that's the opposite way.
但我记得恰恰相反
It's a library to be used for user space programs.
它是给用户空间程序用的库
So not fun.
所以不感兴趣
libkdd.
Uh, parsing kernel data.
解析内核数据
I have no idea where this is used or what it is.
我不知道这个库用在哪 也不清楚它是什么
Um, our good friend, osfmk, uh, open source foundation mach kernel.
嗯 我们的老朋友 osfmk 开源基金会的mach内核
Uh, so this is where everything like
这里汇集了
this is where virtual memory management, task management
这里涉及虚拟内存管理、任务管理
super important stuff is that like
都是很重要的东西
this is a critical part of the kernel that we absolutely will need to know.
这是内核中一个至关重要的部分 我们必须知道
pexpert platform, uh, Interrupt handling, atomics.
Pexpert 中断处理和原子操作
Maybe if we get curious about that
如果我们对这些感兴趣的话
we can dig in there.
我们可以深入研究一下
Security.
安全
This seems kind of interesting.
这看起来挺有趣的
Like, as a security person
作为一名安全人员
this is something that I'd be like, boop, that's, like somewhere I'd want to look.
这东西会让我，一下子引起探究的兴趣
But, like, I can't remember all of what's in here
不过 这里面具体有些什么 我还真记不起来了
but I think it's, like, checks of...
但我觉得应该是些检查……
Yeah, like, security checks and...
对 像是安全检查之类的……
There's ways to specify only binaries that are of a certain hash can get executed
有办法让 只有特定hash值的二进制程序执行
and things like this. There's all kinds of crazy checks
之类的 有各种检查
although I'm not sure if those happen in drivers or not.
但我不确定 在驱动中 是否也会检查
And then our good friend BSD.
还有我们的老朋友 BSD
So then there's a directory
有个bsd目录
in BSD that's the whole half of that BSD kernel.
在这里 几乎包含了 BSD 内核的一半
And then tools, which the interesting thing is here
还有工具目录 这里有趣的是
there's the surprising thing in here is that there are test cases.
这里有一些测试用例
like user space programs that use different system calls and stuff.
比如使用不同系统调用的用户空间程序
So these can be actually a great source for understanding how
因此 这些测试用例是了解如何
do I write some C code that talks to this system call
编写与这些系统调用交互的 C 代码
because you have a test case that literally does that.
因为你有一个实际这样做的测试用例
And so you can yank code from there and actually use that code.
因此 你可以从那里拷贝代码并直接使用
So that's super useful.
真是太有用了
But you will probably spend most of your time in these two directories,
但你大部分时间会在这两个目录里
the BSD side and the OSFMK side.
BSD 部分和 OSFMK 部分
Okay, so we've looked at this.
好的 我们看了这个
We want to understand how system calls work.
我们想了解系统调用的工作原理
What do we do?
我们该怎么做？
What was that?
什么？
Read source.
看看源代码
So we like, let's like click here.
所以 我们点击这里
Find a C file.
找到一个 C 文件
Ooh, there's a man page.
哦 这里有个man文档
Actually, this is interesting.
其实很有意思
Getting ahead of myself.
嘴比脑袋快了
Trying to remember where everything is, but console.
我想想 控制台
I don't know, serial general.
串行接口
Now I'm reading code.
现在我在读代码
Keyboard, starting a keyboard.
键盘 开始启动键盘
Am I gonna I don't know
我会
am I gonna find out where system calls go?
我会找到系统调用的地方吗？
Eventually, I will get
最终 我会
I will read all of the code in some order.
我会按照某种顺序读完所有代码
Eventually, I will make it there.
最终 我会找到
Is that an efficient way of operating?
这样操作高效吗？
No?
不是吧？
What was that?
什么？
Is there a README?
有 README 文件吗？
Ooh, what a good question.
咦 好问题
All right.
好的
Yeah, so first thing
嗯 首先
we need to leverage the tools that we have available.
我们要充分利用现有的工具
I'm not saying my workflow is the best possible workflow.
我不是说我的工作流程是最好的
I think you need to find a workflow that works for you.
我觉得你需要找到适合自己的工作流程
But what you need to be thinking about is
但你需要考虑的是
how easy is it for me to find files of a certain type?
如何轻松找到特定类型的文件？
Or how easy is it for me to search through the source code of looking for a certain thing?
或者说 如何轻松在源代码中找到特定东西？
I don't know if you load this up in Visual Studio Code
我不知道 如果你在 VS Code 里加载这些
if it will work and actually have all the stuff.
是否能正常工作并包含所有内容
Also, because it doesn't know how to compile it
另外 因为它不知如何编译
and you probably can't compile it on your own system
而且你在自己的系统上也很难编译
you don't get any of the nice language server features
所以你用不了一些服务功能
of jumping to definitions and stuff.
如跳到定义处 之类的
I basically, I don't know if you've been able to tell
我不知道你们能不能看出来
but I'm basically more old school in the sense that I
我这块儿比较传统
we'll start with this version, 12.5
我们将从 12.5 版本开始
because I think that's going to be our target for the semester.
因为我认为这将是本学期的目标
I use either a combination of just the editor
我通常组合使用一些编辑器
or the editor and a terminal to grep for things.
编辑器+在终端用grep查找
So if I wanted to know
如果我想知道
are there any readmes?
有没有 README 文件？
I would remember how to do it correctly.
我能想起来怎么弄
And then I would say, okay
然后我会说 好的
there's a readme in ./tools/tests/MPMMTest.
在 ./tools/tests/MPMMTest 里有一个 README
And this is, I think, another thing of, oh, the question is
哦 有人问
is XNU open source?
XNU 是开源的吗？
Yes, you can find everything at
是的 你可以在
https://github.com/apple-oss-distributions/XNU.
这里找到xnu的全部内容
Yeah, good. Look at that question online.
看一下网上的问题
Awesome.
真好
So this is part of, I think, understanding things, being comfortable.
我觉得 逐渐理解未知事物 适应它
You have to fundamentally be okay with not knowing everything.
你要能接受 有不清楚的
Like I look at this, I see, hmm
比如 我看着这个 心想 嗯
should I look up what the acronym MPMM is?
要不要查一下 MPMM 是什么？
No, because I don't care what it is.
不 我不在乎
So I have absolutely no idea what this thing is testing
我完全不知道这东西在测什么
but I don't really care.
但我不在乎
But I've just seen this acronym.
但我看到这个缩写了
Maybe it'll come up later.
也许后面会提到
Like it kind of lodges in your brain, but
有个印象
like, don't worry of like
不用担心
perf index Is it testing the performance of the indexing engine or is it
perf index？ 它是测试 索引引擎 的性能 还是……
I don't care.
我管它呢
I'm just trying to find out where the readmes are.
我只是想搞清楚 README 文件在哪里
to look for Are there any readmes that are trying to get me to the system call stuff?
找一找 有没有 README 文件能帮我找到系统调用的内容？
Tools, LLDB macros.
工具和 LLDB 宏
That sounds interesting because Adam did mention
听起来挺有意思的 亚当提过……
that they have great plugins and macros for LLDB.
他们有很多优秀的 LLDB 插件和宏
Those are actually in there. It is awesome.
那些插件和宏都在里面 很棒
README.DEBUG-kernel.txt
That could be interesting if we're like how do we suppose to do this?
如果是告诉我们怎么调试内核的，那会很有趣
Wait, that can't be right.
（回复评论）等下 这太假了
Is that a fake thing?
假的吧
Multi-Processor of Multi-Mushroom.
多蘑菇 的 多处理器 (MPMM)
That can't be.
这不可能
The multi-processor, I believe.
多处理器 我还能信
I don't know about the MM.
MM 是什么我就不知道了
libkdd
Readme.
说明文件
We could go back and look at the thing and be like
我们可以回头看看这个 想到
okay, what is libkdd?
libkdd 是什么？
OSMFK/tests/readme, libkern/zlib/readme
So you're out of luck in your readmes.
所以 很不幸 readme 里没想要的
You've readme failed, I think.
readme这招失败了
What was it?
什么？
Oh, with an iname?
哦 试一下 iname？
Okay, so iname being case independent.
好的 iname 表示 不区分大小写
No, because they're sane people.
不行 因为他们是正常人
They don't have readmes as undercase.
他们不会把说明文件设置成小写
Oh, you're just guessing. Okay.
哦 你猜的  行吧
Macintosh Page Memory Management.
Macintosh 分页 内存 管理
That could be.
可能是
I'm responding to Twitch like a good streamer.
我在回应 Twitch，像一个好主播一样
So now what? We just quit?
然后怎么办？放弃了？
Ah, Google.
啊 谷歌
We have everything here. The source is here.
都在这里 源代码在这儿
Isn't it?
是吗？
I read one command.
我看了个命令
Boom.
grep for syscall.
grep 查 syscall
Sorry, am I in front of a class?
我是在课堂上吗？
Yes, I'm in front of a class
是的 我在课堂上
but I can't show you because the class is stuff.
但我不能给你们看 因为课堂规定
No, no, you're fine. You're not distracting.
不不 没事 不打扰
We are streaming. This is what we do.
我们在直播 这很正常
Okay, so building up a grep can be a pain.
好的 写一个 grep 命令可能很烦
So what do we want to do?
怎么做？
-R *, so –R recursive, star everything in the current thing.
-R 表示递归  * 代表当前目录下所有内容
I'm in the root here.
我在根目录
I do this, and it's going to be all hell will break loose, right?
执行它 肯定会乱成一团 对吧？
Why is all hell breaking loose?
为什么会乱成这样？
Yeah, lots of files
是的 有很多文件
but also lots of stuff I don't care about,
同时有许多我不关心的内容
like things in, for instance, all the things at the start.
比如 一开始的所有这些东西
Do I care that build/dst/usr/include/mach?
我关心这个吗？
We didn't see build in that list, but if we...
我们在列表里没看到 build 不过……
Do I actually have a clean?
我有实现 clean 吗
That's interesting.
挺有意思的
Yeah, now it's not in there.
对 现在没有了
But the build directory is where everything gets built when I do make.
运行 make 时 所有东西都在BUILD目录里构建
So it's saying, like, binary things match.
所以它会匹配一些二进制程序
Like, of course. Like, we're compiling a bunch of things
当然了，因为我们要编译很多东西
and a bunch of object files and linking them together.
还有很多object文件 然后把它们链接在一起
syscall will be absolutely all over the place.
syscall会遍布各处
Okay, so I can grep for syscall.
好的 我可以查找syscall
Cool.
不错
And so I deleted the build directory.
我删掉了BUILD目录
You can also...
你还可以……
There's ways, I can't remember it.
有办法 但我忘了
Maybe I should just search for this.
也许我该查一下
Isn't there a way to exclude a directory?
有没有办法排除一个目录？
Yeah, --exclude-dir.
对 用排除 目录
Okay, cool, so we can do that.
好的 这样也行
Probably don't care about the tools directory either or the tests.
tools和tests目录也不重要
I don't know
我也不清楚
do I really care about that?
我真的需要管那个吗？
Or tests.
或者tests
Look at this, I'm so much faster than Googling.
看 比谷歌快多了
Okay.
好的
Now I have a bunch of stuff.
现在有很多线索
So I have stuff in
有的在
because I'm looking at this here, just the left-hand side.
我在看左边这部分
I have stuff in BSD.
在 BSD 目录里
I have stuff, oh
还有
I may have gone too fast.
翻得可能太快了
I have stuff in security.
在 security 里也有
So of these directories we're looking at
所以 这些目录中
based on what we just read from the README
根据 README 里的内容
which of these are more likely to have the thing that we're looking for?
哪些更可能包含我们要找的东西？
OSFMK and what else?
OSFMK 还有呢？
BSD.
Yeah, I'd probably
嗯 我大概会
can you do it like that? Yeah.
你能这样做吗？ 没问题
So I'd probably look at those as a starting point
所以我大概会从这些开始看
because those are kind of the core things.
因为这些算是核心的东西
Now it could be, oh, ah, well, that's nice.
哦 啊 这挺好的
So somebody has a much better approach.
有人有个更好的方法
So here we have interesting things.
这里有些有意思的东西
So we have BSD.
我们有 BSD
BSD apparently has its own conf directory.
BSD 有自己的配置目录
So maybe we'd want to look in there and see what, Like
也许我们可以进去看看 比如
if this is something we should be ignored.
看看这是否需要忽略
We have nfs_syscalls.c.
我们有 nfs_syscalls.c
There.
就这儿
Let's see.
我们看看
skip_syscall.
Oh, well, this looks nice.
哦 这个看起来不错
bsd/dev/arm/systemcalls.c.
Should we look there?
要看看吗
Yeah, that looks pretty good.
嗯 这看起来不错
Okay, because I'm not a monster I'm going to use my editor.
我不傻 我会用编辑器看代码
Now, how do I...
现在 我该怎么
No, I want to change the text's.
不 我想改文字的
Sorry, I always have to look this up.
对不起 我总得查这个
Emacs change font size all frames.
Emacs 调整所有窗口的字体大小
Changing font size.
调整字体大小
Current buffer, but I want all buffers.
当前缓冲区 但我希望调整所有的
change font size all buffers
修改所有缓冲区字体大小
Control X, Control Plus.
Control X, Control +
That's what I do.
我就是这样做的
All right, fine.
好吧 行
For you all, I will do it.
为了你们 我会做
Okay.
好的
Okay, so we were looking at tmp/building-xnu
好的 我们要看 tmp/building-xnu
12, wait, wait.
12 等等
What?
什么？
No, that's my own thing.
不 那是我自己的东西
That's funny.
真有意思
Okay.
好吧
We're in here, we were in
我们在这里，我们之前在
and we saw a file in, what is it, bsd/dev/arm/systemcalls.c
我们之前看到一个文件，bsd/dev/arm/systemcalls.c
Okay, so BSD, 12.5, XNU, BSD, dev, arm.
好的  BSD 12.5 XNU dev arm
Let's look at arm 64
我们看 arm 64的
because that's what we're using
因为我们用的这个
and so if we're gonna go to an architecture specific file
所以我们要查看架构特定的文件
we might as well go to the one that, ah
那我们就看那个
but maybe it's not here.
可能它不在这里
Okay, so, But this seems interesting, SYSCTL_INT.
好的 这个看起来挺有意思的 SYSCTL_INT
Oh no, that's, anyways
哦 不管了
we could dig in and look up this.
我们可以深入研究一下
This is like a key value store to like specify
这存着一个键值对 用来指定
things that an admin can change, like
管理员可以更改的项目
and root can change, like variables directly in the kernel.
还有root可以更改的 内核中变量
Anyways, this is, we could dig in and figure that out
总之 这个我们能搞明白
but we're trying to dig in and figure out something else.
但我们正在尝试弄清楚其他的东西
Yeah, I'm in the wrong file
是的 我进错文件了
because there is no system calls.
因为这里没有系统调用
So I'd go arm64.
所以我要去 arm64
When I grep for syscalls in here.
我在这搜索一下syscall
There's none in here.
这里没有
So, okay.
好吧
Let's briefly scan through systemcalls.c in ARM.
我们快速看看 ARM 目录里的 systemcalls.c
Maybe it gives us something interesting.
也许会有一些有趣的东西
I'll just kind of vaguely...
我随便看看……
Okay.
好的
I already see something interesting.
我已经发现一些有趣的东西了
Does anybody else see something interesting here?
有人看到吗
What was it?
是什么？
syscall.h.
Yeah, that seems interesting.
是的 这挺有意思的
Now, we'd have to look up the exact compilation.
现在 我们得查一下具体的编译原理
I can't remember.
我想不起来
I mean, the...
我是说 这个……
Having the angular brackets around this means it's a library function
用尖括号括起来 表示这是一个库函数
that the compiler searches certain paths
编译器会搜索特定路径
of figuring out where this file is.
来找到这个文件
Whatever, I'm just going to search for it.
不管了 先找一下syscall.h
And I will fail.
还没找到
Oh, I actually do know why.
哦 我知道为什么
Why is it failing?
为什么会失败？
What?
什么？
I'm in this directory.
我在这个目录里
This is the kernel.
这是内核
We can't have external dependencies, otherwise we're...
我们不能有外部依赖 否则就……
Hmm?
嗯？
Say it again?
再说一遍？
I can't hear you.
我听不见
Yeah, so...
嗯 所以……
So the file, okay
这个文件
so we know two things.
我们知道两点
We know this file has to exist for that thing to compile.
这个文件必须存在 才能编译
I guess we've technically never seen this kernel compile
准确来说 我们还没看到 这个内核成功编译
but we can switch to the version that does work
但我们可以切换到可以工作的版本
or I can port those changes over very quickly
或快速移植这些改动
and we can prove that this kernel does compile.
我们能证明这个内核可以编译
But this file does not exist in the source.
但在源码中没有这个文件
Is it auto-generated?
它是自动生成的吗？
It must be.
是的
The compilation process must be auto-generated it
编译时 肯定会 自动生成它
and why can't we find it?
为什么找不到它呢？
Because we haven't tried to generate it.
因为我们还没生成它
No, we did try to generate it
不 我们试过生成它
but then I cleaned it
但之后我清理了它
and deleted everything to make it easier.
全删了 方便筛选
So, let's rebuild it and see what happens.
所以 我们重构建一下看看
Okay.
好的
ah it still won't work because it doesn't build.
它还是不行 因为编译不了
Awesome, awesome, awesome.
太棒了 太棒了 太棒了
What?
什么？
Wait, wait, sorry, what? Say that again?
等一下 抱歉 什么？再说一遍？
It has its own kernel headers in there.
里面有自己的内核头文件
Yeah.
嗯
So the problem was I was running make inside of the XNU thing
问题是 我是在 XNU 里面运行 make
which is running their make
它也在运行 make
but I needed to go out one more to run mine make that does everything that it needs to do.
但我需要到外面一层 运行我的 会执行它需要的全部的那个
I really hope this is the reason this will be silly.
希望就是这个原因 不然我就搞笑了
Computer's getting hot.
电脑变热了
I mean, you get into like the bootstrapping paradox problem,
我是说 虽然会遇到引导悖论这样的问题
but fundamentally, no.
但其实不会
Boom, there we go.
好了 搞定了
See, and everything's in build
你看 都在build里
so this makes sense.
这说的通了
So what this tells us is there must be some process
所以 构建时 一定有一个过程
that like as a pre-compilation step,
就像一个预编译步骤
and which kind of makes sense, right?
这合情合理 对吧？
Probably you want system calls defined maybe where they're necessary.
可能想 只定义必要的系统调用
and then collating them all from the whole kernel
然后从整个内核中汇总所有调用
and creating one syscall.h that everyone else can include.
创建一个 syscall.h 供其他部分引入
I don't know if it's actually done like that, but
我不知道是不是真的这样做 不过
yeah.
嗯
So let's look at
那么我们来看看
so now we do need that build file
所以我们需要BUILD里的文件
so I was incorrect.
我之前错了
So we need build
所以我们需要build
我们去 dst/usr/include/sys 里面看看
Okay, cool.
好的 不错
These make sense because we know BSD is very similar to Linux.
有道理 因为 BSD 和 Linux 很相似
We're very, we know a lot of the Linux system calls.
我们对很多 Linux 系统调用都很熟悉
Link, unlink, we can just kind of scroll through these.
链接、取消链接 我们可以快速浏览
Oh, interesting.
哦 有趣
Oh, so there's a macro so you can know the maximum sys call.
哦 原来还有个宏 可以让你知道最大的系统调用
Cool.
不错
And apparently some of these system calls you used to actually be able to call.
显然 这里有些你熟悉的 确实能调用
You can read the book.
你可以读书
The guy talks about these different things.
书里谈到了这些内容
But okay.
好的
So let's say we want to go to
比如 我们想去
there must be like a sysopen.
肯定有个类似 sys open 的东西
So okay, we want to go to sysopen, right?
我们要看 SYS_open 对吧？
We know this macro.
我们知道这个宏
I hope too. It didn't, but...
它没如我所愿
Well, this may be too much, but...
嗯 这可能会太多了 但……
I mean, I know this should be in BSD or not.
应该就在 BSD  也许不是
Oh, interesting.
哦 有意思
Okay.
好的
That's going to take longer than I thought.
这比我想象的要费时间
Telemetry?
远测？
Yeah.
嗯
Okay, this is weird.
这太奇怪了
Okay.
好的
So four, five, one, wow, random hashes.
451 哇 随机哈希
That doesn't seem fill me with confidence.
这似乎没怎么增加我的信心
Okay.
好的
Oh, oh, there we go.
哦 有了
Okay, so we got a hit, right?
好，我们找到了一个线索
So at least the four, five, one.
至少 这个451
The intuition was
想法是
if we search
如果我们搜索
the 451 is not something that just like randomly occurs as you're coding,
451 编码时 不是瞎写的
except in these hashes, right?
除非它是hash出来的
So the intuition was, okay
所以直觉是
if we look for that
如果我们查找它
maybe that will give us some clue
也许那能给我们一些线索
and we see something with telemetry.
然后通过 telemetry 我们发现了些线索
So we at least see, okay there's this init sysent.
我们找到了 init sysent.c
And what's this in?
它在哪个目录？
Build/obj
Okay.
行
So this includes some stuff.
所以这里引入了一些东西
The casts are bogus but we'll do for now.
"这些类型转换不对劲 但先这样用"
I don't, what is that? Like, you know, who needs ...
我不，谁需要
structs Okay.
一些结构体 好的
Aha. Okay. So this is cool.
啊哈 好的 这很酷
So now we get the zero, the one, the exit, the fork, the read, the write, the open.
现在我们找到了0、1 退出、fork、read、write、open
And now we can maybe look at this as like sy_call_t * ... 12
我们可以把这个 (sy_call_t *) open...12  看作 open
no idea what this is but
完全不知道这是什么 但
what's this called?
这叫什么？
Requires, oh, interesting.
需要这个 哦 有趣
So where does this open come from then?
那这个 open 是从哪里来的？
Okay. Do we want to find telemetry?
我们要找 telemetry 吗？
I feel like this will be way easier to find.
我觉得这个会更容易找到
Okay.
好的
See, I think what this is doing without digging in is that like
还没深入看它，它的功能看着像是
no I don't know.
我不知道
I think it's like
我觉得可能是
it may need to work with 32 bits
它可能需要 32 位的数据
and require weird system call stuff.
并且需要一些特殊的系统调用
So the system calls are different on different things
所以不同架构上的系统调用不一样
and you need different like handlers,
需要不同的处理程序
but yeah, you could definitely.
不过确实 你肯定能
Yeah.
嗯
Okay.
行
So I had another trick that I've forgotten.
我还有一个技巧忘记了
Ah, there we're looking somewhere.
啊 找到了一些
Okay, so I looked for just the telemetry we were interested in
我只找了感兴趣的telemetry
because we know that's some function.
因为它肯定是个函数
So the way I always think about this, right this guy's like this.
我是这样想的
If we have this .c file, this telemetry pointer
这个文件里的telemetry 指针
which is probably the exact function we want to call on this system call,
很可能是 使用这个系统调用时 要调用的函数
is... defined somewhere in here, right?
应该是在这里的某个位置 定义的 对吧？
Somebody is defining this thing
有人在这里定义了这个东西
but I don't know exactly where.
但我不知道具体在哪里
And I also don't necessarily want to go to the definition
而且我也不一定非得去看函数声明
because if I go to the definition
因为就算看了函数声明
I also want to go to the actual implementation.
还是要看函数实现
I'm more interested in reading the implementation.
我对实现更感兴趣
So one trick is to do like
所以一个技巧是
like look for something that looks like a function definition
比如说 找看着像 函数声明 的
or at least the call to the function.
或像 函数调用
And so we see this nice, let's see.
于是我们看到了这个
Yeah, I think it's the syscalls.master.
我觉得它是 syscalls.master
Did we look for anything with the name of syscalls in it?
我们有没有找过文件名里有 syscalls 的
I don't think so.
我觉得没有
what was it?
你说什么
kern/syscalls.master
but them in bsd. you forgot to say bsd
在bsd里，你忘了说bsd
Ah, and, anybody see this?
啊 还有 有人看到这个了吗？
makesyscalls.sh
So our first thing was we didn't
首先 刚刚我们没有
grep for just anything with any file with the name system call in it.
直接查找文件名中包含 syscall 的
That would have, we would have definitely found that here.
那样的话 当时就能找到这个
Yeah, so this is interesting.
是的 这很有意思
This is,
这个是
you could probably look over this of how they actually generate things.
看这个，你们能大概知道他们是怎么生成这些的
I don't care about it so much.
我不太在意这个
Wait, that's not what I want.
等等 这不是我要的
No, that's definitely not what I want.
这个更不是
Um, so then you can look for this of like their formats
通过这个 能知道他们的格式
um how they create this.
知道它们的生成方法
Yeah.
对
So, so telemetry is a function that
所以 telemetry 函数
takes in a command, a deadline, an interval, a leeway
接受参数有：cmd、deadline、interval、leeway
and maybe an arg4 an arg5.
可能还有 arg4 arg5
This no syscall stub though. Looks, uh, suspicious.
不过这个 NO_SYSCALL_STUB 看起来有点奇怪
So I don't know what that's going to do, but, uh,
我不知道这有嘛用 但
seems to be not great.
似乎不太对劲
Oh, microstackshot.
哦 微栈快照
Oh, I think I did look up this micro stack shot
哦 我查过这个微栈快照
of like taking a shot of the stack of a process while it's running or something
就是捕获进程运行时的栈状态
to like get telemetry debug information about what's going on.
用来获取调试数据信息 了解发生了什么
Okay, and we have this UIPC syscalls.
好吧 还有 UIPC 系统调用
Interesting.
有趣
Okay, but where, so
好吧 但是在哪里？
Let's at least look at this telemetry
我们先看看这个telemetry
and see if there's anything else interesting
看看有没有其他有趣的
of like an actual implementation of that function.
比如 这个函数的实现
Okay.
好的
I think that's us right there, right?
这个就是我们之前看的，对吧
Yeah.
是的
Ooh.
哦
Oh, this is the other trick.
哦 另一个诀窍是
I just remembered by looking at this.
看到这个 才想起来
The other thing you can do in grepping for a function definition is
找函数声明时，你还可以
for whatever reason this is like Apple style for almost all of their things.
不知什么原因 几乎所有苹果产品 都遵守一个风格
So if you look for the thing you're interested in, like telemetry, parentheses,
当你想查找感兴趣的 比如 "telemetry("
but at the start character so it's at the start of the line you'll often find the definition.
它通常在行首
And that is very helpful.
这非常有帮助
And then we can see
接着我们可以看到
so this takes in a proc pointer p,
这里接收一个proc指针 P
telemetry_args args, ret value, some return value.
遥测参数 args, retval 返回值
So at least just looking at this
所以至少从这里看
this is very weird that these are both unused.
这两个参数都没用到 非常奇怪
Why would it not return anything?
为什么它不返回任何东西？
But so we could at least look at this and say, okay, args command
看到这个 我们知道 这个args->cmd
without even looking at the struct
不用看结构体
we know at least from the documentation that we saw of the system call interface
从系统调用接口的文档中 我们知道
that the first argument was cmd command.
第一个参数是 cmd 命令
Another interesting thing, there's an if def here.
还有一个有趣的是 这里有一个 #if
So depending on how our OS, how...
所以 取决于我们操作系统的设置
We may or may not compile this
我们可能会，也可能不会编译这部分
but then we could also look at the kernel
但我们也可以看看内核
and have to find this telemetry function
找找这个telemetry函数
and maybe see if we even have telemetry.
看看是否有telemetry
So there's these different commands, TELEMETRY_CMD_TIMER_EVENT.
这里有各种命令 比如TELEMETRY_CMD_TIMER_EVENT
This is when I see something like this that's very unique
看到这种非常独特的东西时
I'll know that I can very easily find this header file.
就知道这个头文件很容易找到
If we look at these header files
如果我们看看这些头文件
I don't know if...
不确定...
Oh, kern/telemetry.h is where I guess...
哦 我猜是 kern/telemetry.h
And that's going to be in
它应该在
and I always have to find these.
我总得找一下
I think this is back in our
我觉得是在
in our object dst/usr/include/kern.
No, I'm trying not to swear.
不 我尽量不说脏话
Telemetry.h, OSMFK kern.
Telemetry.h 哦 在 osfmk/kern/
Wow, that's super annoying.
哇 真够烦的
This is the problem when you have these two like I said, the two different worlds.
正如我说的 当有2个内核，就会有这样的问题
Yeah, so this is like a BSD system call interface that's giving you access,
对 这是一个 BSD 系统调用接口 能让你访问
it looks like, to the OS FMK telemetry stuff.
OSFMK 的 telemetry
So what were we looking at?
我们要找什么来着
We were here, we looked here.
刚刚在这，看了这里
Ah, sorry.
啊 抱歉
There we go, okay.
好了
So I just want to see where this thing is defined.
我就想看看这个东西 是在哪里定义的
There we go.
好的 找到了
So this is where things are defined.
他们定义在这里
So we have these telemetry command timer event.
这里有 这些 TELEMETRY_CMD_TIMER_EVENT 之类的
Other question, is this is user space going to be able to access this header file?
还有个问题 用户空间能访问这个头文件吗？
uh no usually so the idea is like
嗯 通常不行 是这样的
you need from user space to be able to call this
你需要 用户空间能调用这个
so there must like these commands and these arguments
所以这些 命令 和 参数
have to be defined somewhere that user space can find them
必须定义在 用户空间能找到它们 的地方
and oftentimes it's like exactly these files um
很多时候就是这些文件
yeah it was kind of a trick ish question
嗯 这其实是一个有点搞的问题
but the anyways the point is
但重点是
because if we call a command to the kernel
如果我们对内核调用一个命令
we need to know what these
我们要知道
arguments are going to be that we're passing in as command
我们作为命令传入 的参数是什么
And this, so there's an enum of telemetry PMI.
这有个枚举类型 telemetry_pmi
There's, now this stuff I think gets yanked out.
我估计 这部分会被去除
I think this is part of the compilation process when creating header files,
我估计 这是生成头文件时 编译过程的一部分
this XNU kernel private.
这个 XNU 内核私有
This stuff all gets redacted
这些内容都会被删除
when it makes a public kernel thing.
等它变成一个公共的内核时
But obviously since we're in the kernel
但显然 因为我们在内核里面
we need to see these files.
我们会看到这些文件
telemetry_ast, that seems very interesting.
telemetry_ast 看起来很有趣
I would guess there's bugs in here.
我猜这里有些 bug
just from looking at this
光是看看这里
this seems very complicated.
这看起来很复杂
Yeah, so telemetry timer event
遥测计时器事件
and I bet there would be since we're in kern
我们已经在kern里了，我猜
we're already in telemetry.h
我们已经在 telemetry.h 里了
there's a telemetry.c.
肯定有一个 telemetry.c
So this is literally just taking the arguments from the args,
这就是从args中提取参数
the deadline, the interval, the leeway
截止时间、间隔和容差
which I think we saw in our syscall master.
我觉得我们在syscall.master中见过这些
Deadline, interval, leeway.
截止时间、间隔、容差
Yeah, not only complicated, but maybe also under executed.
复杂 但可能调用不到
Yeah, yeah. Who's calling this stuff?
是的 要看谁在调用这些？
The tricky thing, of course, to like
关键在于
this is why you have to be very careful being like
这就是为什么你必须非常小心
I'm going to study this code and then find a bug and get rich.
我研究一下这段代码 找个漏洞 然后变富
Then you find it and then you realize like
等找到漏洞了 才发现
oh actually there's a policy in place that like
有机制确保
only root processes can talk to the syscall, which happens.
只有root进程才能和这个syscall交互，这完全有可能
So you have to be careful.
所以要小心
You want to test it.
你要测试一下
that you can actually call this from user space.
确保你能在用户空间调用这个syscall
This is why it's super important to verify your assumptions before diving in too much
所以 在深入研究前 先验证你的假设 十分重要
and being like this code looks sus as the kids say.
这段代码看着很, 以年轻人口吻说, 可疑
Okay.
好的
Where was that C code we were looking at in BSD?
我们刚看的那段 BSD 里的 C 代码在哪儿？
Was that sysgeneric? Yeah.
是 sys_generic.c 吗？对
So that's the telemetry interface.
这就是telemetry接口
Well, I think this is every system call.
我觉得 这是每个系统调用
This is why it's unused.
所以不用它
I think their system call interface
我认为他们的 系统调用 接口
basically always gets the current proc struct in there.
总会获取当前的proc结构体
and then passes the arguments as a pointer in the second arguments.
然后将第二个参数里的指针 作为参数传递下去
So yeah, we can look at this telemetry timer event,
我们可以看一下这个telemetry_timer_event
a deadline, an interval, and a leeway
包括截止时间、间隔和容差
all of which are unused.
这些都没有使用
That seems very weird.
这看起来很奇怪
Why do you have code that has functions that get passed in that are never used?
为什么会有这样的代码 接收参数 却全都不用
So if telemetry needs timer arming record is true
如果 telemetry_needs_timer_arming_record 为真
then set it to be false.
就将其设置为假
Take some sample of the current thread
从当前线程中取样
and do this and then return zero.
执行这个操作并返回零
Interesting.
有趣
What was that?
什么？
pmi_setup
pmi_ctr、period（传入的interval）
Yeah, another if def
又一个 #if
so you've got to be careful.
所以要小心
Remember, again, the configuration thing.
再提醒一下 要看配置
It's like every time you look at some configuration thing
每次看到要看配置的
before getting excited that you found a bug
在激动 自己找到 bug 前
you need to double check and verify these things.
你需要再次检查一下 这些东西
This is interesting.
真有意思
Well, it's a const, but a character pointer.
嗯 它是 const 的一个字符指针
Those always are...
这些总是
Okay, so pmi_ctr.
好的 pmi_ctr
So there's another command inside here, it looks like, that we can...
这里又有命令，看起来我们可以
This is coming from args-deadline
这个来自 args->deadline
which is then a switch statement on there
这里用了一个 switch 语句
which tells me that there's some other functionality we can target through here.
这说明 能在这里 追踪到别的功能实现
We need this, sample_all_...
我们需要这个。 sample_all_...
MT, oh yeah, it is this microstack shot.
mt 哦 对了 这是微栈快照
The name, so it's setting up some name
名字 它在设置某个东西的名字
and this seems weird.
这看起来有点奇怪
Can name come from us? No.
名字可以由用户提供吗？ 不能
It's either...
要么……
Okay.
好的
So, yeah, this is some micro stack shot thing.
所以 这是一个微栈快照
Interesting.
有意思
Telemetry PMI unlock.
That would be another thing to...
它又是
Okay, so there's some mutex here.
好的 这里有个互斥锁
Yeah, I don't know.
是啊 我也不知道
You always think like could you mess with that?
你们总是会想 能搞搞它吗？
don't know.
不知道
But anyways, okay, so we at least found we found a system call.
但总之 我们至少找到了一个系统调用
We found like the entry point.
我们找到了入口点
We figured out how to get there.
我们知道了如何到那里
Did we learn anything about the kernel here?
对于内核 我们有学到什么吗？
It sus.
可能有洞
Every, all code, all code is sus.
所有代码都可能有漏洞
Yeah.
嗯
But now that we know this, and so like
不过现在我们知道这些了
if we were doing this as a target, right
如果把这个作为目标
taking notes on this I'd be like, oh, great
知道这些后 我会想 太好了
syscalls.master has like the list of all the system call numbers
syscalls.master 里有所有系统调用的编号
and the functions
和函数
and then you'd probably say most of these UIPC, right?
你大概会说 大部分这些 UIPC
This was where, wait, it wasn't.
这里 等等 不是这里
Where was the telemetry?
telemetry在哪儿？
sys_generic.c.
Yeah, sys_generic.c was in where that telemetry is in
对 telemetry 在 sys_generic.c 里
in bsd/kern.
它在 bsd/kern中
So probably other things are in here.
这里可能还有其他东西
Like ledger.
比如ledger
Omnibus system call for ledger operations.
用于ledger（分类账）操作的一个综合系统调用
See, that's also seems sus.
这也有可能有洞
Like who's doing these ledger operations?
谁在进行这些账本操作？
But the double sus means to me that like
但 更让我怀疑的是
that somebody else has learned that like
可能其他人也发现了这一点
it's just not used.
只是它没被用
So anyways, that's interesting.
总之 这挺有意思的
See, it's like if defs of debug, like
看，#ifdef 调试语句
so you think like you leave debug statements in your code
你可能会在代码中留下调试语句
they leave if defs of debug structs definitions in their code
他们在代码中用#ifdef 留下调试结构体
which probably are not
这些可能
ah, interesting. So copyin, this is, we should
有趣 copyin 这是 我们应该
Since we're digging in we can look at this.
既然在深入研究 我们可以看看这个
I think we can already, where?
我觉得我们现在可以
It's exactly like copy_from_user in Linux
这和 Linux 里的 copy_from_user 一样
but I do not recall the semantics.
但我记不清它的细节了
I think,
我觉得
yeah, so len is an int
对 len 是一个整型
and sizeof(len) from arg3.
然后 从 arg3 拷贝出 sizeof(len) 个字节 到 len
So what, arg3 must be a pointer to len.
所以 arg3 一定是一个指向 长度值 的指针
And I guess we can look at ledger and say like one, two, three.
我们可以看看ledger  一、二、三
Yeah, I can't remember what
对 我记不清
I can't remember what C adder T stands for
我忘了 cadder_t 是什么
what the C stands for
c 表示什么
but it's like a user space pointer.
但它就是一个用户空间的指针
And this is like the type they use to define that.
他们用这个 定义这种类型
Yeah, that's interesting.
嗯 这挺有意思的
Yeah, we can look at
嗯 我们可以看看
and we can maybe hopefully use my tricks if I wasn't full of.
如果我没记错 也许可以用我的方法
There we go.
好了
So now we can go look at this
现在我们可以看看这个
but at least we know the semantics here
至少我们知道了这里的语义
the user address, the kernel address, and the number of bytes, copyio.c.
用户地址 内核地址 和 字节数，在 copyio.c
This would probably be something we look in our heads of, like I should understand how this works.
这大概是我们需要记住并理解的
Also...
另外...
So we don't do any copy if the number of bytes is zero.
所以 如果字节数为零 就不进行复制
This copy validates function is very interesting because
这个复制验证函数非常有趣 因为
so you have to remember the security boundary here
你必须记住这里的安全边界
from user space and kernel space, right?
用户空间和内核空间之间的 对吧？
So if we're copying something from user space
所以 当我们从用户空间复制东西
but the user has tricked us
如果用户欺骗了我们
and given us a kernel address
并给了我们一个内核地址
and now we're copying kernel data somewhere
现在我们拷贝的是内核某处数据
and that maybe makes it back to user space
这些数据可能会传回到用户空间
that would be a clear vulnerability.
这将是一个明显的漏洞
So we want You have to be very careful when doing all this stuff.
所以我们在做这些事情时必须非常小心
I assume this stuff's been tested
我估计这些功能已经测试过
but I don't know.
但我不确定
You're free to look at this and poke around here.
你可以自由探索
Because like this copy validate
比如 这个 copy validate 函数
what's this do?
它有什么作用？
What are these arguments?
这些参数是什么？
Whenever I see like flags to a function
每当我看到函数中的flag
this is like kind of makes me skeptical.
这让我有点怀疑
And I'm like what do these arguments mean?
然后我就想  这些参数是什么意思？
Can I grep for every single instance of copy validate
我能用 `grep` 查找每一处 `copy validate` 吗
and look to make sure that they're using the right arguments for that context?
并确认 它们在上下文中用的是正确的参数吗？
And can I do that quickly?
我能快速做到这一点吗？
Just like, manually.
就像手动一样
That's a way I would do this.
这是我处理的方式
Yeah, interesting.
嗯 挺有意思的
If the result is EXDEV
如果结果是 EXDEV
I have no idea what that means.
我真不知道那是什么意思
Oh, maybe.
哦 大概是吧
Then copyin_kern so it's a
然后执行 copyin_kern 复制到内核
otherwise user enable access.
否则 执行 user_access_enable
That sounds interesting.
听上去挺有趣的
_bcopyin from the user address to the kernel address
_bcopyin 从用户地址 复制到内核地址
and then user access disable.
再禁用用户访问
Might as well look to see what this is.
不如看看这是什么
Ooh, ARM stuff, great.
哦 ARM 的东西 真好
What the heck does this do?
这是干什么的？
Nice.
好
So what is pan?
那 PAN 是什么？
Making sure that we can't access kernel stuff
确保我们不能访问内核的东西
or user space stuff from the kernel.
并且 内核不能直接访问用户空间的东西
So this is funny.
所以说这挺逗的
This is just a thing that does nothing
这个东西什么也不做
if this is not available on the system of the target.
如果目标系统上 不支持这个PAN 的话
Oh, Privilege Access Never.
哦 特权 访问 永不
I thought you said network.
我以为你说的是网络
I know that doesn't make sense
我知道”网络“不对
so I didn't go with it until I looked at it.
所以我查了后 才确认
Cool.
太好了
Yeah.
嗯
Maybe.
可能吧
You looked at all of them?  Ah, damn.
你都看过了？啊 糟了
We could have found something right on stream.
我们本可以直播时 一起发现些什么
Okay.
行
Maybe.
可能吧
Okay, yeah.
行 嗯
So zero means privileged reads and writes are not disabled.
所以 0 表示 特权读和写 未禁用
One means privileged reads and writes are, yeah, okay.
1 表示特权读写 已禁用。好的
Now this makes sense.
现在这说得通了
So does everyone understand what this is doing?
都明白这是怎么回事吗？
Well, now I feel like we need to just see if Justin is full of it or not.
我觉得 是时候看看 贾斯汀是不是在吹牛了
What is it, like dash A for more context?
是加上 -A 来获取更多上下文信息吗？
I guess they're all in this file
估计都在这个文件里
so we could have just looked at them.
所以我们可以直接查看这些内容
I don't know.
我不知道
Could any of these fault?
这些会出问题吗？
Yeah. Right.  yeah. That makes sense. Okay.
有道理
Um, Yeah, here it's done very easy,
嗯 这里实现得很简单
done very easy, done, done, done, done.
都很简单
That seems weird.
这确实有点奇怪
bcopy is like their raw copy.
bcopy 是原始的复制函数
I don't fully understand what it actually is.
我还没完全搞清楚它是什么
Interesting.
挺有趣的
The question is, why do you need different ones?
问题是 为什么需要不同的版本？
These are almost identical in terms of their semantics
这些在语义上几乎相同
from what I'm seeing.
依我看
Well, let's look at these bcopies then
我们来看看这些 bcopy 函数
I remember I looked at them before.
我记得之前看过这些
I think they're just raw kernel like just copy memory around
我以为 他们就是内核里拷贝内存数据的
but you don't want people to use them.
但你不想让用户用这些
You want them to use the other thing.
你希望他们用其他的
Yeah, and I think they're assembly.
对 我想这些是用汇编写的
Ooh, look at this.
哇 看看这个
See, look at it.
你看 就是这个
You all learned assembly
你们都学过汇编
and it's useful.
这就用上了
There we go.
就是这样
Okay, OSFMK, ARM64.
好的 在 osfmk/arm64
machine_routines_asm.s
All right, look at this.
好 看看这个
Okay.
好的
ARM64 stack prolog, push frame.
ARM64 栈序言， 压栈
I guess these are macros, I assume.
我觉得这些是宏
Copy IO recover range.
复制 I/O 恢复区间
Move zero into X4
将 0 移入 X4
the total bytes copied.
复制的总字节数
loop load a byte from the user source.
循环 从用户处 加载一个字节
So dereference X0, which is user address.
解引用 X0 这是用户地址
ldrb. See remember when I said they use all this crazy stuff, right?
看吧 我提到过 他们会用这些东西 对吧
Wait, this is X0. Oh, this is a post increment operation, right?
等一下 这个 X0  哦 这是一个后索引操作 对吧？
So it's dereference X0, move that byte into W5
所以是 先解引用X0 将内存里的字节 放到w5
and then add one to X0.
然后再将 X0 加 1
So store byte from user space, load a byte from user space,
从用户空间取1字节
store byte to the destination.
存到目标地址
So then store, it's actually really nice.
这样其实真的很好
This is pretty compact.
这相当简洁
I like it.
我喜欢这个
So then store W5 that byte to X1 and then increment that.
然后把 W5 里的字节 存到 X1  再递增 X1
So you have both of your pointers moving.
这样两个指针都在动
Increment byte copied.
增加 已拷贝字节计数
So then X4 is what?
那么 X4 是什么呢？
Zero, one, two, three.
零 一 二 三
Oh, X4 is always set to zero.
哦 X4 置零了
That's going to be our return address.
它是输出参数
cbz
This byte is null. We're done.
如果这个字节是空，就完成了
So compare. Oh, so this is like a copy until null.
哦 这相当于 一直复制到null字节
Is that?
是这样吗？
The idea.
它的意思
This makes a thousand times more sense.
这相当合理
Okay.
好的
So yeah.
没错
So everyone get that?
大家都明白了吗？
This is b copy in string, not instruction.
这个是 b 拷贝 字符串，不是 指令
Amazing.
太棒了
But see, we learned it by reading the code.
我们通过读代码学到了
This is what you have to do sometimes.
有时候这是必须的
But now I'm curious. Let's just like look at what's, what, the ending is.
现在我很好奇 我们看看结尾是什么
So compare x5 with null.
将 x5 和 null 比较
If it's null
如果它是 null
then branch to done
就跳转到 done
which loads let's see what, oh, store x4 into x3.
它会 把 x4 存到 x3 指向的内存
So put the number of bytes read where x3 points
所以 将 x3记录的 已读入字节数
because x3, 0, 1, 2, 3 is the actual
因为 x3 是这个 actual
so this is the number of bytes that we copied in.
所以这就是我们复制的字节数
And then... Move x5 into x0, which was our...
然后 将 x5 赋值给 x0
Yeah, the result of the comparison which if we're done is going to be zero.
对 如果拷贝完了 比较结果（x5）就是零
Right?
对吧？
Yeah, because that's the byte that we read in.
对 因为我们读入的就是null
Wow, that's a hyper-optimization.
哇 真是优化到了极致
But rather than setting...
但与其设置...
That is weird. Why not just set...
这真奇怪 为什么不直接设...
Oh, okay.
哦 好的
and then pop the frame and then epilogue,
然后弹出栈帧 执行尾声
and then compare x4 to x2, and then branch back to loop.
然后比较 x4 和 x2  再跳回循环
Otherwise, oh, the name was too long.
否则 报错 名字太长了
Ah, that's interesting.
啊 真有趣
So, okay, let's look back at our copyio.
好的，我们回过头接着看 copyio
In string, now that we know the semantics here
现在我们知道了 这个instr 指的是 字符串
which makes sense why it's almost exactly identical except for that
这就解释了为什么它几乎是完全一样的 除了那个地方
Yeah. Okay.
好的
So copy in and then result.
copyin 返回结果放到result
Okay.
好的
So yeah, the vulnerability, I mean this is like a classic
这像一个经典的漏洞
str, what is it? strncpy that doesn't put the null byte at the end of the string,
str什么来着？strncpy 不在字符串末尾放null字节
right?
对吧？
So you can call that and if strncpy
如果你调用 strncpy
you give it exactly the number of bytes
你给它确切的字节数
or it copies up to those number of bytes
或者 当它拷贝到那些个字节
and If it doesn't get to the null byte
并且如果中间没遇到null字节
it won't include it.
它就不会加null字节
And so you can have a null terminating string.
你就可以得到一个 不以空字节结尾的字符串
So that's a similar problem that they have here, right?
这里也有类似的问题 对吧？
_bcopyinstr
If you end up copying number of bytes
如果拷贝到一定的字节数
you will get this E name too long
会返回一个错误码 E name too long
that gets returned as an error code from here.
会从这里返回这个错误码
But then you need to be very careful
但这里需要特别小心
that everyone that calls this actually checks the return value.
确保每个调用者都检查返回值
So maybe we should check that.
所以也许我们可以检查一下
and I don't care about those ones.
我不关心那些
And let's give ourselves like four lines after of context
我们在后面加上四行上下文
because that should be good.
那样会很好
Okay, well, that looks at an error.
好的 这里看到一个error
Oh, see it, it actually tells us exactly what we just learned, right?
看 它说了 我们刚学到的内容
E name too long is a term of length bytes have copied in
ENAMETOOLONG 表示 拷贝len个字节
but the null pointer was not encountered.
但没有遇到空指针
That does not require raising, CPU_DTRACE_BADADDR and we press on.
这不会引发 CPU_DTRACE_BADADDR 会继续执行
That seems weird.
这看起来有点奇怪
Okay.
好的
Okay, but this is in dtrace
好的 这是在 dtrace 里
and you need to be root to use dtrace anyways
而且使用 dtrace 需要 root 权限
but that could be something interesting.
但这可能很有趣
Maybe there's something there.
说不定有什么漏洞
Okay.
好的
Oh, there's an interesting there's this dtrace_copyinstr
哦 有个有趣的东西 dtrace_copyinstr
which we probably don't care about.
不过我们可能不太关心
Yeah, so here's like
是的 这里有
I don't know, nullfs, is that literally like dev null?
nullfs 不知道是不是类似 linux 里的 /dev/null
I think this actually may be the code that does dev null.
这可能是实现类似 /dev/null 功能的代码
copyin error.
copyin 出错的情况
Yeah, this is something you could probably write a, CodeQL query for
这时候可以写一个 codeQL 查询 看看
I'm just not very good at that.
我不太擅长这个
I just like looking at the code
我喜欢读读代码
because the error checking is going to be the next thing that happens.
因为接下来会进行错误检查
So we see that there.
我们看到它在那里
If error, if not error
如果有错误 如果没有错误
if error return error
如果有错误就返回错误
this seems weird but it seems fine.
看着挺奇怪 不过应该没问题
That seems interesting.
这看起来挺有意思的
copy in string
i don't know what this does but it continues executing
我不知道这是干嘛的 但它继续执行下去了
that could be something interesting to look at for somebody
这可能挺有趣的
and uh so this is nfs
这就是 NFS
and the just like on linux right
就像在 Linux 上一样
if you're creating some virtual file system you have to create
如果你要创建一个虚拟文件系统 你得先
you have to handle all the virtual file system operations
你得能处理 虚拟文件系统的所有操作
open close whatever
比如打开、关闭等
Yeah, this seems sketchy.
是啊 这看着不太对
Maybe it's at the end of a loop
可能是循环的末尾
and then at the top of the loop it'll check error
然后在循环的开头 它会进行错误检查
which we just don't have enough context to tell
我们目前没有足够的上下文来判断
but it seems weird.
但看起来有点奇怪
Yeah, we could do that
嗯 我们可以那样做
but I guess I didn't look at how many there are.
我没数清楚有多少个
Maybe I should have done that before looking at this.
也许我应该先搞清楚 再来看这个
We'll do this for like one more minute.
我们再看一分钟
That's an error check. That's good.
有错误检查  很好
有检查错误 很好
That's an error check, that's good.
检查了错误 好的
copy_error is not equal to zero.
拷贝结果 不为零
Okay, so this is the interesting one you need to look at, right?
好的 这就是你要特别关注的 对吧？
Because this is checking if copy error is named too long
因为这个检查了 ENAMETOOLONG
and it only errors out there
只在那出错
but if it is named too long
如果为真
then it also sets the last one to be null.
它会将最后一个字节设置为 null
So that's what we're trying to find.
这是我们想要找的（没置null的话）
Error.
出错
Again, another, looks like another safe mark of a null byte.
又一个 看起来也安全设置null了
I kind of assumed they would fix all of these
我猜他们把这类问题都修复了
but you never know
但谁知道呢
and this is how you find stuff.
这就是怎么发现问题的
Error check.
检查错误
I guess maybe what you could do
我觉得你可以
is write a codeQL query that checks for the other copy stuff
写个codeQL查询 检查其他 copy 函数
that it's using the same, like, Mac, Apple, and everything.
检查一下其它用这个的，像 mac、苹果等
Yeah, where I could see this be an error, right
对 我看 出错的情况 大概像
is if somebody used copy in
如果有人之前用的copyin
and then just changed it to a copy in string
然后直接改成了copyinstr
without thinking about the semantics there
没考虑语义问题
and then that causing a problem.
这样就会出问题
Yeah, that's like these are all fine.
是的 这些都没问题
That could be interesting depending on what this is, but...
这具体看情况 可能会很有趣
I would assume maybe after all of these case statements
我想 在这些 case 语句之后
that one of these is checking the error
其中一个是在检查错误
but this is another interesting one at the end of something.
这个也挺有意思，像是在什么的末尾
Oh, here, maybe at this.
哦 这里 在这里检查的
I mean, I didn't think that we would find just a bug a clear bug after this
我不认为 我们这样 能直接找到一个明显的bug
but it was worth looking at
但值得一看
because I think it's a fun.
因为我觉得很有趣
Okay, this is hard to read.
这很难读
This looks like it's not checking.
看起来这里没有检查
There's a debug and a resolver and then nothing.
这里有一个调试器和解析器 之后就没有了
Maybe it's doing it afterwards.
可能之后会处理
kern_credential sounds interesting.
内核凭据 听起来很有趣
VFS lookup.
VFS 查找
I gotta, I don't know.
我不知道 得看看
Anyways, okay, cool.
不管怎样 好的 不错
So we practiced recon and now we learned a lot about XNU, hopefully.
我们进行了侦察演练 希望能对 XNU 有更多的了解
My intuition here is that there's probably not anything here.
我觉得这里应该没什么bug
If there was, somebody would have already found it
如果有的话 早就有其他人发现了
because these are very shallow bugs, right?
因为这些bug都很明显 对吧？
The copying in from user space happens at the very first part of the system call.
从用户空间的复制 发生在系统调用的最初阶段
So testing this stuff is very, very easy.
所以测试这些内容非常简单
You just need to be able to talk to the system call.
只要能和系统调用交互就行
So it's not a bug I would expect like later on in the code, but.
所以我不认为能在代码中找到这样的bug
Hey, you know, whatever.
嘿 总之
If one of you finds some stuff with this, that's great.
如果你们找到bug了，那太好了
And that'll be good.
那很好
Cool. Thanks for class.
谢谢大家的参与